<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The remedie of reason not so comfortable for matter, as compendious for memorie. Wherein the ignorant may gather instruction, the learned confirmation, all men consolation. By Charles Gibbon.</title>
            <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11820</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838882</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838882</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 544:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The remedie of reason not so comfortable for matter, as compendious for memorie. Wherein the ignorant may gather instruction, the learned confirmation, all men consolation. By Charles Gibbon.</title>
                  <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Outlines, syllabi, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:1"/>
            <p>The Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Reaſon: <hi>Not ſo comfortable for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> as compendious for <hi>memorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the ignorant may gather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, the learned confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all men conſolation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Charles Gibbon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Be readie alwaies to giue an anſwer to euerie man that asketh you a <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the hope that is in you, &amp;c. <bibl>1. <hi>Peter</hi> 3.15, 16.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>If any man think that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to knowe. <bibl>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Orwin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:2"/>
            <head>To the right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir Robert Iarmin Knight: <hi>And to the VVorſhipfull Master Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> Blagge Eſquier: perfect fruition <hi>of infinite felicitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Alomon,</hi> that moſt renowmed and royal King, waying the wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this world by the weight of his wonderfull wiſedome, could no leſſe but redouble his words, and ſaie: <hi>Vanitas vanitatum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.33.</note> 
               <hi>vanitas vanitatum, &amp; omnia vanitas.</hi> Which ſeeing it is ſo (Right Worſhipfull) it behoueth euery one of vs, not ſo much to auoid the cauſes that maie prouoke vs to vanitie, as to practiſe all the meanes that may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vs to pietie; and to walke with ſuch foreſight in this terreſtriall pilgrimage, as wee may haue fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of felicitie in the coeleſtiall Paradiſe; according to the counſell of our Sauiour Chriſt, who willeth vs firſt to ſeeke the kingdome of GOD and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes;<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3 2.</note> and not diſſenting from the ſaying of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Eccle. 1.2.</note> who perſwadeth vs to ſet our affections on things that are aboue, and not on things that are on the earth. Inſomuch, as all our knowledge is but vaine that is ſeduced with vanitie; all our wiſedome
<pb facs="tcp:3272:3"/> is but meere follie that is carried away with earthly cogitations; yea, all our dooings deteſtable that tend onelie to temporall diſpoſitions: for there is none to be deemed wiſe indeed, that will not beſtowe his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the treaſure of Gods word, conſidering it is ſo precious that it ought more to bee deſired than gold, yea than much fine gold;<note place="margin">Pſal. 19 10. Pſalm 119.97.</note> and it is ſo delectable, that in ſweetnes it exceedeth the honie &amp; the honie combe; wherein <hi>Dauid</hi> did oppoſe his whole delight. And it is ſo expedient for vs to profite therein, as he that hath much may yeeld ſomewhat, ſithence he that hath leſſe ſhall not bee excuſed with nothing. The Lord will looke for tenne talents where he left fiue,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.22.</note> and wil pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him that maketh no profite where he beſtowed one. Hereof it is I haue proceeded in this enterpriſe, &amp; beſtowed my time to the benefite of others; which although it bee not comparable to any commendable woorke, yet that is not excuſable for any to detract his duetie, ſeeing God will accept a mite of a willing minde; neither ought to be contemptible amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers though all bee not currant, for the building is furthered by inferiour helpes though it be framed by finer heads. Againe, the world is now growne into his laſt age, wherein ſects, ſchiſmes, and errors doo ſpread, and ſinne and iniquitie aboundeth; inſomuch as (I feare me) it is with many of vs in <hi>England,</hi> as it was with the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> they loathed <hi>Manna</hi> that fell from heauen for the ſuſtenance of their bodies, and too too many of vs doo little regard that ſpiritual <hi>Manna</hi> (the word of God) that is ſent for the ſuccour of our ſoules. Hereof it is I haue made choice of your good Worſhips, and preſented my labours to your
<pb facs="tcp:3272:3"/> godlie patronage, aſſuring my ſelfe that as you bee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers and followers of Gods word, ſo you will be defenders of the fruites of the ſame, and rather be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrers than defacers of a forward action: not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but your Worſhips will well accept of it, as a worke importing and proceeding of good will, by the conſideration of that excellent example of the poore widowe, preferring the ſimplicitie of the giuer before the ſufficiencie of the gift; knowing that the imperfection of the preſent may bee couered by the preſumption of the Poet; and I may ſay in the want of well doing, <hi>Eſt voluiſſe ſatis.</hi> Thus being loath to be too tedious in my Epiſtle, hauing obſerued breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in all the whole booke, I referre the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof to your graue cenſures, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting my ſelfe to your good curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, &amp; committing your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to the protection of the Almightie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips to command,</hi> Charles Gibbon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Chriſtian and <hi>curteous Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that doth publiſh a matter to the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many, the ſame requireth to be done, not lightlie but deliberatlie; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it is ſubiect to ſundrie Cenſures, and in reading and iudging all are not <hi>Candidi Lectores.</hi> In regard whereof, (good Christian Reader) I haue publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed my paines to thy profite, and preſented the liking of it to thy looking ouer, hauing (as nigh as I may) not onelie cut off all ſuch occaſions, as might cauſe cauillation; but alſo miniſtred ſuch matter as concernes our conſolation: and although it bee not poliſhed preciſelie for the expectation of the curious, yet it is finiſhed plainlie for the information of the ſimple. Now it may bee, there bee many that will vſe obiections againſt the triple forme of this treatiſe; becauſe no Arte hath reduced all things (and rightly) to <hi>Dicotomies.</hi> True; but wiſedome may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue much compendiouſly, and yet profitablie: beſides although I haue framed it as an eaſie enterance for the erudition of the ignorant, J haue not excluded what may further be added by the conſideration of the learned: and albeit much more might be inſerted in many places for prolixitie, yet much leſſe I feare me is obſerued of the moſt part for their vtilitie. Some will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a more direct placing of thinges in their order. Certes that is well placed that is well applied; and thoſe that do more respect the manner of placing than the matter it ſelfe, may be noted in the number of thoſe, who would haue the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> to precede, and not to follow the booke of <hi>Iob;</hi> making a ſcrupulous queſtion without cauſe, when wee all knowe they are both included in the Scriptures, &amp; containe comfortable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for our ſaluation. Some will not like ſo many diuers ſorts of
<pb facs="tcp:3272:4"/> ſundrie things congeſt together in one heape, other will require more perspicuitie, ſome one thing, ſome another. Inſomuch, as he that expecteth to pleaſe the opinions of all people, muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refraine from open publication of any thing, or referre himſelfe to their generall diſpoſitions in iudgement: and this is the common ſucceſſe of acceptance; many will commend it, moſt will miſlike it, fewe will followe it. But as my meaning was to profite the ſimple by the ſetting foorth of it, ſo I ſhall perſwade the godlie to a good liking of it: and as for the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward I will not refell their fooliſh questions in diſputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, knowing what the Apostle <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, that fooliſh and vnlearned queſtions ingender ſtrife. So,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.23.</note> wiſhing all to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure others by the met they would receiue themſelues, and ſo to report as they expect in any enterpriſe, I both ſubmit my ſelf to reprehenſion, ſo it be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; and commit euery one to his owne liking, ſo it bee indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. <hi>Vale. Bury S. Edmond.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>Charles Gibbon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:5"/>
            <head>O Lord</head>
            <l>Aduance thy glorious Gospell heere: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>No papall parts may once appeere. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Giue peace &amp; plentie alwaies there: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Let not the foe procure our feare. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Inlarge her life whereby we ſtay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And make vs thankefull euery day. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:5"/>
            <head>The remedie of <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>EVerie mans knowledge ought to be
<list>
                     <item>reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</item>
                     <item>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<list>
                           <item>towards God,</item>
                           <item>to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That hee preſume not to vnderſtande aboue that which is meete to vnderſtand. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3.</item>
                                 <item>That according to his knowledge hee ſhewe the ſame in his life and conuerſation; or els his great knowledge will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn him: <hi>Lu.</hi> 12.48.</item>
                                 <item>That as hee hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the gift, hee mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſame to others. 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 4.10.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> He that would attaine to an effectuall knowledge of God, muſt remember
<list>
                     <item>his precepts. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>his promiſes. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>his threatnings. <hi>Luther.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The eternal power of God maie be knowne
<list>
                     <item>by the reuelation of his word,</item>
                     <item>by the creation of the world,</item>
                     <item>by the conſideration of al his works.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The infallible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God may appeare vnto vs by the preſeruation
<list>
                     <item>of <hi>Daniel</hi> in the lyons denne. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.16.</item>
                     <item>of <hi>Ionas</hi> in the whales bellie. <hi>Ionas.</hi> 1.15.</item>
                     <item>of the three <hi>Children</hi> in the fierie ouen.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:6"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The prouidence of God is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for he worketh
<list>
                     <item>by meanes:</item>
                     <item>without means:
<list>
                           <item>For meat is a meane to ſerue his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of health and life here: hee that contemneth to eate, becauſe his prouidence is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and infallible, doth contemne his prouidence.</item>
                           <item>For if it were ſo that meate could not be had, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould we not tye his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to this meane; for without meate God can helpe and giue health and life here.</item>
                           <item>For his power and wiſedome is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, &amp; therfore we ſhould depend vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, euen when al is cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>againſt meanes:</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The exceeding mercie of God is made manifeſt vnto vs in the Scriptures
<list>
                     <item>By the miraculous examples of compaſsion.</item>
                     <item>By the manifold words of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</item>
                     <item>By the death of his onelie ſonne for our propitiation.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:6"/>
               <item>He that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſts the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth him to be
<list>
                     <item>Loue,</item>
                     <item>Truth,</item>
                     <item>Power,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> wherin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts all the hope of poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:
<list>
                                 <item>Becauſe of his great loue hee ſent his onlie ſonne to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death for the remiſsion of our ſinnes.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe hee promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the loue of his ſonne, pardon to all poore ſinners ſo oft as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it in faith, with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trite hart.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe he is as true of his promiſes, as hee is able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them; &amp; as he is of power, ſo wil he do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer pleaſeth him.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The ſuperabundant loue of God appeareth to vs in this, that he ſent his owne Sonne
<list>
                     <item>for our Redemption.</item>
                     <item>for our Iuſtification.</item>
                     <item>for our Sanctification.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The ioyes of heauen prepared for thoſe that loue God, are ſuch as
<list>
                     <item>the eye hath not ſeene,</item>
                     <item>the eare hath not heard,</item>
                     <item>the hart cannot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue.</item>
                  </list> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:7"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Euerie one ought to knowe the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in beleeuing
<list>
                     <item>a God,</item>
                     <item>of God,
<list>
                           <item>Is to beleeue he is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie true and almightie God; this faith is Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall, for ſo the diuelles beleeue as well as the wicked.</item>
                           <item>Is to beleeue all is true that he ſaith in the Scriptures of him; and ſo doo the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Chriſtians aſwell as the good, vnleſſe they bee Heretickes.</item>
                           <item>Is to loue him, and to truſt in his goodneſſe, and in beleeuing to ioyne our ſelues to him by loue and obedience; this faith is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall, onely proper to the elect (who liue by faith).</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>in God,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> It is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for vs to ſaie, we
<list>
                     <item>know God,</item>
                     <item>loue God,</item>
                     <item>feare God,</item>
                  </list> vnleſſe we keep his commandements. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> GOD ſheweth vppon earth
<list>
                     <item>mercie,</item>
                     <item>iudgement,
<list>
                           <item>wherein conſiſts our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</item>
                           <item>wherwith he puniſheth the wicked.</item>
                           <item>whereby hee preſerueth the godlie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>iuſtice,</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 9.24 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:7"/>
               <item>God often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times croſſeth and puniſheth man vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth
<list>
                     <item>for his owne glorie,</item>
                     <item>for example to others,</item>
                     <item>for triall of his faith,</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> as appeare
<list>
                     <item>by the blindman. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.3.</item>
                     <item>by the Galileans. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3.</item>
                     <item>by <hi>Iob</hi> that pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent man.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> God in times paſt ſpake and preached to his people
<list>
                     <item>by Dreames.</item>
                     <item>by Viſions.</item>
                     <item>by Reuelations.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>GOD hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed three pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces for all perſons.
<list>
                     <item>The ioyes of heauen</item>
                     <item>The paines of hell
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> for the godlie;</item>
                           <item>for the wicked;</item>
                           <item>for both.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The vſe of the earth</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>GOD is worthelie ſaid to bee
<list>
                     <item>rich in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</item>
                     <item>mightie in iuſtice,</item>
                     <item>bountiful in grace,</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> in that he
<list>
                     <item>reſpecteth the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble freelie.</item>
                     <item>iudgeth the wicked iuſtlie.</item>
                     <item>ſaueth ſinners pitiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. <hi>Barnard.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> GOD requireth no more at our hands but theſe three things,
<list>
                     <item>Feare.</item>
                     <item>Obedience.</item>
                     <item>Loue.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:8"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> God ought to be loued of vs,
<list>
                     <item>with all our hearts,</item>
                     <item>with all our ſoules,</item>
                     <item>with al our ſtrength. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.</item>
                  </list> All thinges worke for the beſt to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue GOD. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> God is loued ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually three man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of waies:
<list>
                     <item>entirelie,</item>
                     <item>orderlie,</item>
                     <item>pretiouſlie.
<list>
                           <item>In hauing a good will to him, reioycing great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie hee is ſuch a one as he is.</item>
                           <item>In referring ourſelues &amp; all that wee haue to him, in ſuch manner &amp; meaſure as he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</item>
                           <item>In louing him ſo dearelie that for no cauſe, wee would looſe him or his loue, but wiſh ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to loſe our liuing, life, and the loue of all the world.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Loue is the end of the Commandement. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.
<list>
                     <item>Loue cannot bee without a good conſcience.</item>
                     <item>A good conſcience cannot bee without faith.</item>
                     <item>Faith cannot bee without the word of God.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> We ought continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie to bee thankfull to God, becauſe
<list>
                     <item>of him</item>
                     <item>through him</item>
                     <item>for him</item>
                  </list> are all things. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:8"/>
               <item>True thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in theſe three things.
<list>
                     <item>Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</item>
                     <item>Abiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</item>
                     <item>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> Becauſe in recounting Gods excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding benefits he hath done for vs, wee ſhall finde the better occaſion (if we well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider) to be the more thankfull for them, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, which made him in feruencie of ſpirit burſt forth with theſe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: <hi>What ſhall I render vnto the Lord for al his benefites bestowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me?</hi> Pſal 116.12, 13, 14.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe if wee meaſure the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Gods benefites with our deſarts, we ſhal find our ſelues not worthie of the leaſt, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our imperfections we are no better than Abiects, which we ſhould not onelie acknowledge, and ſaie with the ſame Prophet, <hi>Lord what is man that thou art ſo mindful of him?</hi> Pſal. 144.3. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in regard therof ſay (with him) <hi>I will not die but liue</hi> (to this end) <hi>to declare the works &amp; goodnes of God he hath done for me.</hi> Pſal. 118.17.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe it is not enough for vs to receiue Gods benefits &amp; be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thereof, but alſo we are bound to make others to profite thereby and praiſe God, as the ſame <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mograph</hi> did. <hi>Come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and hearken all ye that feare God, and I will tell you what he hath done to my ſoule.</hi> Pſal. 66.16.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:9"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> We ought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie to haue the feare of God before our eyes;
<list>
                     <item>becauſe it is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſedome. <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.10.</item>
                     <item>becauſe it cauſeth vs to depart from all euill. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.23.</item>
                     <item>becauſe his mercie is on ſuch from generation to generation. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.50</item>
                  </list> It was the treaſure of Hezekiah. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 33.6.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> There be three kinde of feares.
<list>
                     <item>childlie feare,</item>
                     <item>ſeruile feare,</item>
                     <item>naturall feare,
<list>
                           <item>This appertaineth to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, who feare God onelie for his goodnes, without any ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter reſpects. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.31.</item>
                           <item>This is proper to the wicked, who feare God onely for his puniſhment. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 17.3.</item>
                           <item>This is common to both, for faith oftentimes faileth the very elect. <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.26.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> The feare of God (as S. <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith) is
<list>
                     <item>The water of wholeſome wiſedome.</item>
                     <item>The Well of life.</item>
                     <item>The beginning of knowledge.</item>
                  </list> He that hath this feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes,
<list>
                     <item>his waies are beautifull.</item>
                     <item>his pathes are peaceable.</item>
                     <item>his footſteps are vnmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> This may inforce vs to feare God;
<list>
                     <item>becauſe he is ſaid to be terrible, and a God of reuenge. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.</item>
                     <item>becauſe his houſe ſhalbe ſoone ouerthrowne that feares him not <hi>Eccle.</hi> 27.3.</item>
                     <item>becauſe he is ſuch a one as is able to caſt both bodie and ſoule into hell fire. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:9"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> God repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him of three things:
<list>
                     <item>That he had made man on the earth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6.</item>
                     <item>That he had made <hi>Saule</hi> King. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11.</item>
                     <item>That he had ſent euil to the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> 2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 24</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> God neuer repenteth, although it ſeemeth ſo to mans iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, when any thing goeth contrarie to his temporall election.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe his eternal cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell is immutable. <hi>Hoſe</hi> 13.14.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe he is not man that he ſhould repent. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 15.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe all his workes are exceeding good. <hi>Ec.</hi> 39.16</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>GOD ought to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped of vs
<list>
                     <item>with our hearts</item>
                     <item>with our mouthes</item>
                     <item>with our workes
<list>
                           <item>ſincerelie;</item>
                           <item>boldlie;</item>
                           <item>according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie;
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> Becauſe with the heart man beleeueth vnto righteouſnes. <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.10.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe with the mouth he confeſſeth vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe by workes hee ſheweth the fruites of his faith and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.17.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> In the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God this is to be conſidered:
<list>
                     <item>If we acknowledge him in our hearts, and denie him with our mouthes, or any of our members, he wil denie vs; and this is no better than idolatrie. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.9.</item>
                     <item>If we drawe nie him with our lips, and are farre from him with our hearts, he will not heare vs; for this is meere hypocriſie. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18 41.</item>
                     <item>If wee doo workes, and they bee done without faith, hee will not accept them, for it is but iniquitie. <hi>Ro.</hi> 14.23.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:10"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> Whatſoeuer wee neede, we muſt require the ſame of God by praier. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he knoweth our want before wee aske, yet we muſt praie:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe hee hath commanded we ſhould. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.39.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe wee continuallie want that grace which hee hath promiſed to giue.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe the diuel is buſie. <hi>Leaſt wee fall into temptation.</hi> Luk. 22.40.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> Praier is very expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and profitable: (conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our whole ſaluation conſiſteth in the calling vpon the name of God) for thereby he is whollie preſent with vs by his
<list>
                     <item>fatherly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence,</item>
                     <item>infallible power,</item>
                     <item>infinit good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<list>
                           <item>By the which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually watcheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</item>
                           <item>By the which he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth and ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our weakenes, being euery mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t readie to periſh.</item>
                           <item>By the which hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth vs into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour beeing miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie laden with ſin.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> Our praiers are to bee vſed generallie
<list>
                     <item>at all times;</item>
                     <item>in all places;</item>
                     <item>for all perſons,
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe the Lord hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to heare vs at what time ſoeuer we call vpon him faithfullie. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.19.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he is euery where, <hi>whether ſhall I goe from thy ſpirit</hi> (ſaieth <hi>Dauid.) Pſalm</hi> 139.6.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe it is our duetie to pray one for another. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.16.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:10"/>
               <item>In our praier we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<list>
                     <item>in whoſe preſence we ſtand,</item>
                     <item>to whom we ſpeake,</item>
                     <item>what we deſire,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> That ſeeing wee ſtand in the preſence of God, (to whoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie ſo innumerable thouſands of Angels doo aſsiſt and be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect) wee maie haue a reuerent regard of his maieſtie in preparing our ſelues to praier, leaſt therby we tempt him. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 18.22.</item>
                           <item>That ſeeing we inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him that knoweth the ſecretes of our hearts, (before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing is more odious than hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) we call vpon him in truth, leaſt he reiect our ſuites.</item>
                           <item>That ſeeing praiers at adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture are vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table (which proceed more of cuſtome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lips, than of zeale from the heart) wee aske thoſe thinges which be moſt to the glory of God, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, leaſt we aske &amp; eceiue not. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.2.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:11"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> We muſt offer &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our praiers
<list>
                     <item>faithfully without doubting;</item>
                     <item>charitablie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wrath;
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe the Lord hath not promiſed to graunt, but onelie to ſuch as beleeue to obtaine: and therefore he ſaith, <hi>Whatſoeuer you deſire when you praie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that you ſhall haue it and it ſhall bee done vnto you.</hi> Mar. 11.24.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe we cannot bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of Gods fauour, vnles we forgiue (which is after the maner of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament vnto vs) Hereof ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt <hi>When you pray forgiue that your father maie forgiue you.</hi> Mar. 11.25.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth perſeuerance in our praiers, according to that ſame ſaying of S. <hi>Paule. In due ſeaſon we ſhall reape if we faint not.</hi> Gala. 6.9.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>inceſſantlie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fainting,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> We muſt not offer our praiers
<list>
                     <item>to any idoll;</item>
                     <item>to any earthlie man;
<list>
                           <item>For it is abhomination in the ſight of God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.15.</item>
                           <item>For curſed is hee that putteth his truſt in man. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.5.</item>
                           <item>For Chriſt is our onelie Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.3.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>to any heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sainct;</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:11"/>
               <item>Our praiers muſt be vſed &amp; offered to God by Chriſt Ieſus.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> Becauſe all power is giuen into his hands. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.22.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe in him the father is well pleaſed. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3 17.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe without him wee can doo nothing. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.5.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>He that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual praier, muſt haue
<list>
                     <item>a liuelie feeling faith. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145</item>
                     <item>peace and loue with his nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</item>
                     <item>a life anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to this faith. 1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 3.</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> leſt it be
<list>
                     <item>hindered. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</item>
                     <item>not regarded. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.</item>
                     <item>turned into ſinne. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> Our praier hath his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from Chriſt, or els it could not preuaile:
<list>
                     <item>For he was made ſinne for vs, that wee might bee made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of God. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</item>
                     <item>For to him that worketh not, but beleeueth in him that iuſtifieth the vngodlie, his faith is counted for righteouſnes. <hi>Rom</hi> 4.5.</item>
                     <item>For wee being iuſtified through faith, haue peace towards GOD through him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> Chriſt Ieſus maie verie fitlie be called
<list>
                     <item>our eye;</item>
                     <item>our mouth;
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe by him wee ſee the father.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe by him wee ſpeake to the father.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe by him we offer to the father.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>our hand.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:12"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> The Lord will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies preſentlie heare our praiers, or grant our requeſts;
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe he will trie our faith and patience. Hereof ſaith <hi>Dauid, I waited patiently for the Lord, and hee inclined vnto me and heard my crie.</hi> Pſal. 40.1.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe they are impertinent: <hi>For wee knowe not what to pray as wee ought.</hi> Rom. 8.26. And therefore wee aske and haue not, becauſe we aske amiſſe. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.3.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe they accord not with his pleaſure: <hi>For this aſſurance wee haue, if we aske according to his will he heareth vs.</hi> 1. Iohn 5.14.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> To this end in praier wee ſhould lift vp
<list>
                     <item>our eyes,</item>
                     <item>our handes,
<list>
                           <item>That they may not incline or bee carried away with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Hereof ſaieth <hi>Dauid, Turne awaie mine eyes from regarding vanitie.</hi> Pſal. 119.37.</item>
                           <item>That wee ſhould remember our ſelues to be farr off from GOD, vnles wee lift vp our hearts alſo on hie and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the ſame Prophet, <hi>To thee haue I lift vp my ſoule.</hi> Pſal. 25.1.</item>
                           <item>That therby we ſhould know, if our harts be not farre from terreſtriall cogitations, wee ſhall hardly receiue any cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall conſolations.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>our hearts,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:12"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> We maie lawfullie in praier aske corporal benefites of God:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe wee ſhould thereby knowe that he is the author &amp; giuer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſhould not onelie be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him for it, but thereby to ſeeke, loue and worſhip him.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe we ſhould be perſwaded of his good prouidence towards vs, in that hee hath not onelie promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he wil neuer faile vs. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7. but alſo hath an outſtretched hand to helpe them that call vpon him.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe our faith of reconciliation and remiſsion of ſinnes, ſhould be exerciſed through the asking of theſe corporall things.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> The feruent praier of the righteous much auaileth, not onelie for themſelues, but for others:
<list>
                     <item>At <hi>Moſes</hi> praier the plague ceaſed. <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Helias</hi> cauſed great plentie of raine. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 17.</item>
                     <item>Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> deliuered her and her people. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 14.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> We ought to referre all our praiers, requeſts and dooings to Gods good pleaſure, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the example
<list>
                     <item>of Chriſt,</item>
                     <item>of Dauid,
<list>
                           <item>when he was crucified without cauſe by the Iewes. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.4.</item>
                           <item>when hee was diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of his kingdom by his ſonne. 2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 15.26.</item>
                           <item>when he was afflicted moſt grieuouſlie by Sathan. <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.7. &amp; 13.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>of Iob,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:13"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/> The meanes wherby we are drawne to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, is
<list>
                     <item>Faith.</item>
                     <item>Hope.</item>
                     <item>Charitie.
<list>
                           <item>The chiefeſt of theſe is Loue; becauſe it ſerueth here and in the world to come. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/> The work of a true faith is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon
<list>
                     <item>things paſt:</item>
                     <item>things preſent:
<list>
                           <item>We beleeue the death of Chriſt is paſt.</item>
                           <item>Wee beleeue at this preſent hee ſitteth at the right hand of his father.</item>
                           <item>Wee beleeue that Chriſt ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>things to come: <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/> Faith doth grow and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in vs three manner of waies:
<list>
                     <item>By the hearing of the word of God preached:</item>
                     <item>By the reuerent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe it laieth before our eyes the promiſes which God in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell hath made vnto vs in his Sonne.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe they being right lie receiued of vs, are as pledges and ſeales of the promiſes of GOD, made vnto vs, in his word.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe God hath made an eſpeciall promiſe to vs thereby, that he will heare vs whatſoeuer wee aske according to his will.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>By praier and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:13"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="49"/> A true and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie faith muſt be
<list>
                     <item>ſimple</item>
                     <item>ſound</item>
                     <item>conſtant
<list>
                           <item>in beleeuing</item>
                           <item>in defending</item>
                           <item>in following
<list>
                                 <item>The word of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inquiring or ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in Gods myſtical matters, by humane reaſons.</item>
                                 <item>The truth thereof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inclining or lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the erronious opinions of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of the ſame.</item>
                                 <item>The ſame worde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting, for anie reaſon of mans braine that ſeemeth contrary, nor to be drawn awaie from it by temptations, promiſes, or thretnings either of torment or of death.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Such as will know whether they haue an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall faith, muſt conſider
<list>
                     <item>The fruits of it</item>
                     <item>The triall of it</item>
                     <item>The ende of it</item>
                  </list> is
<list>
                     <item>good works:</item>
                     <item>afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</item>
                     <item>ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> For faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes is dead <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.17</item>
                           <item>For it is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for vs to beleue in chriſt but alſo to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his ſake. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.29.</item>
                           <item>For he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth to the ende (hath this comfort) ſhalbe ſaued. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:15"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/> A iuſtifying faith is knowne by theſe effects:
<list>
                     <item>It bringeth foorth fruites. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.18.</item>
                     <item>It worketh by loue. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.6.</item>
                     <item>It apprehendeth Gods mercie offered in Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/> Faith differeth from Hope, and yet we hope in
<list>
                     <item>things preſent:</item>
                     <item>things paſt:
<list>
                           <item>As when I hope I am in Gods fauour.</item>
                           <item>As when I hope my ſins be forgiuen me.</item>
                           <item>As when I hope to haue eternall life.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>things to come</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/> Charitie is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler vertue, for without it what is 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.
<list>
                     <item>Faith:</item>
                     <item>Knowledge:</item>
                     <item>Martirdome:
<list>
                           <item>It auaileth little though it moue mountaines.</item>
                           <item>It profiteth litle though I ſpeake with tongues of men and Angels.</item>
                           <item>It helpeth little though I offer my bodie to be burned.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> We ought to liue in Loue and Charitie:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe it is the effect and fulfilling of the Commandement or whole Law. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it is a teſtimonie vnto vs of our tranſlation from death to life, whereby wee are made the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God and heires in heauen. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it worketh the cauſe in vs, that God dwelleth in vs, for God is loue, &amp; he that dwelleth in loue dwelleth in God and God in him. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.8.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:15"/>
               <item>Workes of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arrogation are verie friuolous, for our works are in no wiſe auailable to ſaue vs, by reaſon of
<list>
                     <item>Their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection:</item>
                     <item>Gods elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</item>
                     <item>Chriſtes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> Becauſe all our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes is no better than filthie cloutes, (or as ſome write) menſtruous clothes. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 64.6.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe wee ſhoulde then choſe God ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our workes, than he ſhould elect vs of his mere grace, and then grace were no grace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe his Sonne ſhould haue ſuffered in vaine, if wee had anie ſufficiencie of our ſelues.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/> Although workes are not the cauſe of our ſaluation, yet partly they are the effects of it, &amp; good workes are very neceſſarie to be vſed amongſt Chriſtians,
<list>
                     <item>That therby God may be glorified. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16.</item>
                     <item>That by their good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple others may be wonne to the word. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.</item>
                     <item>That by them they maie make their election ſure. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> numbreth three degrees of our ſaluation. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Gods mercie,</item>
                     <item>His righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<list>
                           <item>whereby he fatherlie pitieth vs.</item>
                           <item>whereby he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie protecteth vs.</item>
                           <item>wherby appeareth his conſtant fauour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>His trueth,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:16"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> There bee three cauſes of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the
<list>
                     <item>efficient cauſe,</item>
                     <item>materiall cauſe,
<list>
                           <item>GOD the Father is the beginning of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</item>
                           <item>Chriſt Ieſus is hee, in whom our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is reſident.</item>
                           <item>Faithe is the meane whereby wee appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the ſame.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>inſtrumentall cauſe,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/> S. <hi>Paul</hi> approueth the formall cauſe of our ſaluation to be the free mercie of God: for
<list>
                     <item>whom he predeſtinate he callerh,</item>
                     <item>whom hee calleth hee iuſtifieth,</item>
                     <item>whom he iuſtifieth he glorifieth. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</item>
                  </list> By grace ye are ſaued through faith. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> Although there be many reaſons whereby wee maie aſſure our ſelues to bee elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet wee may brieflie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our election
<list>
                     <item>By the holie Ghoſt, which te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth with our ſpirite that we are the children of GOD. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</item>
                     <item>By the fruites of the Spirit, in hauing good workes, or will to doo well.</item>
                     <item>By remorſe of conſcience, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the lothing of ſinne, and loue of righteouſnes.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/> Election is knowne by theſe teſtimonies. <hi>Beza.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10.11.
<list>
                     <item>Faith is gathered by ſanctification, and by according to the truth.</item>
                     <item>Truth is gathered by calling, through the preaching of the Goſpell.</item>
                     <item>The Goſpell aſſureth vs of a certaine hope of glorification.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:16"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="62"/> Touching Election &amp; Reprobation, this is to be conſidered:
<list>
                     <item>That the onelie will and purpoſe of God; is the chiefe cauſe of both.</item>
                     <item>That his free mercie in Chriſt, is an inferiour cauſe of ſaluation.</item>
                     <item>That the hardning of the heart, is an inferiour cauſe of damnation.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> This vndoubted perſwaſion wee ought generally to haue:
<list>
                     <item>Euerie one is elected or eiected at the beginning.</item>
                     <item>Euerie one is an vnprofitable ſeruant when he hath done his beſt.</item>
                     <item>Euerie one ſhal haue reward according to his worke.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>We ought not to condemne or iudge any to bee reprobate; (albeit to bee without feare of GOD, and reuerence of man, are ſignes of reprobation. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> Becauſe it is a ſecret only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to God, &amp; therfore he hath ſaid, <hi>Iudge not, that ye be not iudged.</hi> Matth. 7.1. Iam. 4.12.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe the Lord is not ſo merciful in forgiuing, as he is miraculous in calling; making of a perſecutor an Apoſtle, as he did by <hi>Paule. Acts.</hi> 9.3.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe the very godly haue been greatly ouergone in this matter, as (that great Prophet of the Lord) <hi>Elias,</hi> in iudging the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 19.10.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/> Theſe 3. ſteppes doo leade vs vnto deſtruction. <hi>Barn.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>The diſſembling of our weakenes.</item>
                     <item>The ignorance of our wretchednes.</item>
                     <item>The excuſing and perſeuering in our wickednes.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:17"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/> The Scriptures are written for vs:
<list>
                     <item>That we might knowe the will of God and followe it.</item>
                     <item>That wee might beleeue that Ieſus is Chriſt the Sonne of God. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.31.</item>
                     <item>That in beleeuing wee might haue life through his name. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.31.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> The whole ſcriptures are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into three parts. <hi>Bar.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Lawe.</item>
                     <item>Prophets</item>
                     <item>Goſpell.
<list>
                           <item>The Lawe</item>
                           <item>The Goſpel</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list> conſiſt
<list>
                     <item>in doing.</item>
                     <item>in beleeuing.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/> This may perſwade vs to beleeue the authoritie of the Scriptures to be true. <hi>Bib.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>The ſecret teſtimonie of the holie Ghoſt in our hearts, which cauſeth vs to conſent thereto.</item>
                     <item>The incomprehenſible Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of God appearing in the ſimple and ſincere doctrine therein.</item>
                     <item>The godlie agreement of all parts together, with the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlie diſpoſition, certaintie, and ſucceſſe thereof.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> The Scriptures do ſet forth vnto vs (amongſt many other) three eſpeciall matters which we ought to remember.
<list>
                     <item>The frailtie of man, and his prone inclination to euill.</item>
                     <item>The iuſtice of God, and his ſeuere puniſhment appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for obſtinate tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</item>
                     <item>The mercie of God, and his free pardon; promiſed to penitent ſinners.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:17"/>
               <item>Euerie one ought effectually to know and ſearch the holy Scriptures, for
<list>
                     <item>Knowledge;</item>
                     <item>Confirmation;</item>
                     <item>Conſolation.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> Becauſe the ignorance of them is the cauſe of all error.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe wee muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue nothing, but that which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued by them. <hi>Acts.</hi> 17.11.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe in them is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained eternal life.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>We may gather know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Scriptures three manner of waies.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> By attendant hearing of the ſame well preached.</item>
                     <item>By diligent reading of the ſame with vnderſtanding.</item>
                     <item>By continuall conference with ſuch as can open the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.30.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/> The word of GOD then draweth vs vnto him, <hi>Bib.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>When it is ſo preached and heard, as we vnderſtand and learne what is taught thereby.</item>
                     <item>When we receiue thankfullie that which is giuen, promiſed, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured therein.</item>
                     <item>When we bee moued with deſire and diligence, to do that which it commandeth.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/> The word of God then hath his perfect worke, when it is
<list>
                     <item>Preached truelie.</item>
                     <item>Beleeued faithfullie.</item>
                     <item>Followed effectuallie.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:18"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/> Such as will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the word of God what followeth.
<list>
                     <item>If the righteous ſcarcelie bee ſaued, where ſhall the vngodlie and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appeare? 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8.</item>
                     <item>Euerie vnfaithfull ſhall die in his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulnes, ſaith <hi>Eſdras.</hi> 2. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 15.4.</item>
                     <item>Euerie vnbeleeuer is condemned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.18. and ſhall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with euerlaſting perdition. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/> Ignorance can no way be excuſable:
<list>
                     <item>For that which maie bee knowne of God is made manifeſt vnto vs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19.</item>
                     <item>For thoſe that knowe not the lawe ſhall periſh without the lawe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12.</item>
                     <item>For the offering for ignorant ſinnes in the Leueticall law, argueth no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe to be admitted. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 4.2.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="76"/> Our Sauiour Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth by the parable of the Sower three vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearers of his word. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.
<list>
                     <item>Such a one as heareth it and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it not, by reaſon the euill one commeth and catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it away out of his heart.</item>
                     <item>Such a one as heareth it and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth it preſently with great ioye, but when perſecution or tribulation commeth, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the word hee is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</item>
                     <item>Such a one as heareth it, but the cares of this world and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfulnes of riches choake it, and the ſame is made vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:18"/>
               <item>We ought to reſort to the Church of God,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="77"/> Becauſe his holie myſteries are there laid open, which are hid &amp; obſcure to manie.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe we may bee vnited and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together by receiuing the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe if the Lord hath promiſed to grant our requeſtes, where two or three bee gathered together in his name, how much more will he bee mindfull of a multitude that ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble themſelues.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> The Church of God hath three ancient and excellent ornaments.
<list>
                     <item>Preaching.</item>
                     <item>Praier.</item>
                     <item>Sacraments.
<list>
                           <item>Preaching inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth faith.</item>
                           <item>Praier increaſeth it.</item>
                           <item>Sacraments confirme it.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>The Church or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to pray for all men, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie difference of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, kind, age, or order: <hi>Beza.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3, 4.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="79"/> Becauſe the Lord by calling of all ſorts, yea, ſometimes thoſe that are the greateſt enemies to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, wil haue his Church gathered together after this ſort, &amp; therfore praiers to be made for all.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe God ſhould not els bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to be the onlie God of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnles he ſhould ſhew his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in ſauing of al ſorts of men.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus ſhould not be ſeen to be the onelie Mediator between God and of all ſorts of men, by hauing taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him that nature of man, which is common to al men, vnleſſe he had ſatiſfied for all ſortes of men, and made interceſsion for all.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:19"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are
<list>
                     <item>Signes or badges of chriſtianitie:</item>
                     <item>Seales or pledges of our faith:</item>
                     <item>Aſſurances of our ſaluation.</item>
                  </list> whereof there be 2.
<list>
                     <item>Baptiſme.</item>
                     <item>The Lords Supper.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/> The Sacrament of Baptiſme, <hi>Bib.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Teacheth vs to put on Chriſt, that his righteouſnes may couer our ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.27.</item>
                     <item>Aſſureth vs wee are ſo grafted into Chriſt, that all our corruption is cleane waſhed away. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26.27.</item>
                     <item>Chargeth vs to mortifie, and die to ſinne, that wee may become his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and liue in mutuall amitie.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/> The Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>Bib.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sheweth vs, that the bodie and bloud of Chriſt crucified, is the onelie foode for the regenerate.</item>
                     <item>Aſſureth vs, that Chriſt is whollie ours, and that by faith our ſoules are fed and nouriſhed in him vnto life euerlaſting.</item>
                     <item>Requireth a thankfull remembrance of his death, with vnitie amongſt brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/> The Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is vnworthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie receiued,
<list>
                     <item>when we receiue it onelie by the viſible ſigne, without regard of the inuiſible grace.</item>
                     <item>when wee receiue it more of cuſtome than good conſideration, or more for feare than good affection.</item>
                     <item>when we receiue it diſorderlie, (beeing dronken) or with a corrupted conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in malice or enmitie).</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/> The Sacrament of the Lords Supper muſt be
<list>
                     <item>receiued reuerentlie:</item>
                     <item>eaten effectuallie:</item>
                     <item>digeſted thankfullie.</item>
                  </list> therefore let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one trie and examine
<list>
                     <item>his knowledge.</item>
                     <item>his faith.</item>
                     <item>his repentance.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:19"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="85"/> Good Miniſters are moſt fit to miniſter the holie Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, yet we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them by the euill. <hi>Articl. Religio.</hi> 26.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe they do it in Chriſt his name, and not in their owne.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe their wickednes cannot take away the effect of the ordinance.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe of Chriſts inſtitution &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſo it be receiued rightly by faith</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Theſe three things are to to bee noted (whereof heretofore there hath arriſe ſome queſtion) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper.
<list>
                     <item>By whom we receiue it.</item>
                     <item>with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we receiue it.</item>
                     <item>How oft wee receiue it.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="86"/> we ought rather to receiue it at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the good Miniſter, if it be poſsible, yet we muſt not reiect the miniſterie thereof by the wicked; ſo it be done for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallie. <hi>Artic. pe.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>we maie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with euerie one, ſo they be not ſuch as are notoriouſlie knowne to be dronkards, adulterers, and ſuch like: for that is prohibited. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</item>
                           <item>we may receiue at al times, ſo our faith and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie bee fit for the ſame; otherwiſe it will turne to our condemnation (ſaith <hi>Paule.</hi>) 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>It is a pitifull, nay rather a peſtiferous thing, to ſee ſuch placed in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, as be
<list>
                     <item>Ignorant</item>
                     <item>Negligent</item>
                     <item>Impudent
<list>
                           <item>in learning:</item>
                           <item>in their calling:</item>
                           <item>in their liuing:
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="87"/> For where there is no viſion the people periſh. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 29.18.</item>
                                 <item>For they are accurſed that doo the worke of GOD negligentlie. <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10.</item>
                                 <item>For their lewdnes maketh the word of God worſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:20"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="88"/> Idle Miniſters, vnpreach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paſtors, and ſuch like, are called nothing els but
<list>
                     <item>blind watchmen. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.9.</item>
                     <item>domme dogges. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.10.</item>
                     <item>ſubtile foxes. <hi>Eze.</hi> 13.4.</item>
                  </list> who deſtroy Gods vine for their own aduantage.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="89"/> Godlie Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors will be ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie carefull
<list>
                     <item>of the ſinceritie of their doctrine,</item>
                     <item>of the integritie of their liues,</item>
                     <item>of all their whole actions,</item>
                  </list> that
<list>
                     <item>it bee agreeable to the word of God.</item>
                     <item>they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable to the ſame word.</item>
                     <item>they bee profitable to the example of others.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/> Theſe ſayings may moue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and ſuch like to be verie
<list>
                     <item>carefull;</item>
                     <item>watchfull;</item>
                     <item>fearefull;
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe they muſt one daie yeeld an account of their ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardſhip.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe his bloud ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds that dies in his iniquity thorow their negligence. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.6.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe an hard iudgement ſhall trie him that beareth rule. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 6.5.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="91"/> Godlie Preachers &amp; Paſtors are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be
<list>
                     <item>accepted</item>
                     <item>loued</item>
                     <item>obeyed
<list>
                           <item>for their office ſake,</item>
                           <item>for their workes ſake,</item>
                           <item>for commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſake,
<list>
                                 <item>Becauſe they repreſent the perſon of God. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.41. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.41.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe they diſpoſe his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes &amp; myſteries. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.13.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe they are appoynted ouerſeers and watchers for our ſoules, as thoſe that muſt yeeld accompt for them. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:20"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="92"/> S. <hi>Peter</hi> willeth preachets, paſtors, &amp; ſuch like, to feed their flock, caring for it: 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 5.2.
<list>
                     <item>Not by conſtraint, but willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</item>
                     <item>Not for filthie lucre, but of a readie mind.</item>
                     <item>Not as though they were lords ouer Gods heritage, but as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to them.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhewed a moſt worthie example to prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers and ſuch like, by his
<list>
                     <item>duetifulnes</item>
                     <item>painfulnes</item>
                     <item>contentment
<list>
                           <item>in preaching:</item>
                           <item>in labouring:</item>
                           <item>in liuing:
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="93"/> For he ceaſed not by the ſpace of three yeares to preach and warne euerie one both night and day with teares. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.31.</item>
                                 <item>For he wrought with his own handes to miniſter to his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, not onelie becauſe he would bee chargeable to none, but alſo to helpe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue others. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12.</item>
                                 <item>For although his liuing was little, yet he well accepted of all eſtates, without coueting any mans ſiluer, gold, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell <hi>Acts</hi> 20.33.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Preachers muſt teach the word of God, whether the people regard it, or no:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="94"/> Becauſe it may be a teſtimonie againſt the vnbeleeuers or neglecters of the ſame at the latter day. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.19.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe the Lord will vſe the means of his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to make the wicked more faultie to proue his. <hi>Iere.</hi> 7.27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Becauſe it is their duetie to bee inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="95"/> The ſpirit of prophecying or preaching is ſometime giuen to the wicked aſwell as the godlie; as appeared by
<list>
                     <item>Caiphas <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.51.</item>
                     <item>Saule. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.10.</item>
                     <item>Iudas the Apoſtle.</item>
                  </list> therefore wee muſt trie the ſpirits whether they be of God. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4 1.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:21"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="96"/> The word of God ought not to be exempted from any eſtate, neither ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned in any perſon, in reſpect of his condition, calling, or vnworthines, profeſſing the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, conſidering God hath called
<list>
                     <item>Plowmen from the fields to be Prophets. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 19.19, 20.</item>
                     <item>Shepherds from the folds to be zealous profeſſors. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.7.</item>
                     <item>Fiſherme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from their nets to be followers of him. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.18.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="97"/> We muſt not condemne, or contemne the Miniſters of God, if by infirmitie they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to horrible offences, for Sathan hath begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the moſt godlie profeſſors: as
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lot</hi> that ancient Patriarke, became inceſtuous. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.30.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauid</hi> that excellent Prophet, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted homicid. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.25, 26</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter</hi> that good Apoſtle, prooued periured. <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.27.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="98"/> It is verie dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to deſpiſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, or conſpire the death of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of GOD; as may appere by theſe three examples.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iezabel</hi> did threaten the death of <hi>Eliah;</hi> yet hee liued and was taken vp into heauen, when ſhe died, &amp; was eaten of dogges. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 19.35, 36.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saul</hi> intended the death of <hi>Dauid;</hi> yet hee eſcaped and became King, but <hi>Saul</hi> procured his owne death moſt deſperatlie. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 31.4. 2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 1.9, 15.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Herod</hi> put to death <hi>Iohn Baptiſt;</hi> but as his deedes were deteſtable before God, ſo his end was ignominious to the world, for he was eaten to death with wormes. <hi>Acts</hi> 12.13.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="99"/> Preachers, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, &amp; ſuch like, of all others, are moſt of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to contempt and enmitie.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe Sathan by policie, procureth many to a diſdaine of their perſons, as a meane to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to a diſliking of their doctrine.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe the Spirits of error are now ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad which wil deceiue the harts of many, and cauſe them to become curſed ſpeakers, (eſpecially againſt Gods miniſters. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2</item>
                     <item>Becauſe theſe are thoſe perilous daies wherin it was long ſithence prophecied, <hi>that manie ſhould be deſpiſers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are good.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:21"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="100"/> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> was three times com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to feede his flocke: which is expounded 3. waies.
<list>
                     <item>with ſound doctrine.</item>
                     <item>with honeſt life.</item>
                     <item>with good hoſpitalitie.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Bar. Ich.</hi> 21.</item>
               <item>This worde <hi>(behold)</hi> doth commonlie import ſome great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto vs, as it is vſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt at his
<list>
                     <item>Natiuitie:</item>
                     <item>Paſsion:</item>
                     <item>Second comming:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="101"/> Behold, (ſaith the Angel to the Shepheards) I bring you glad tidings, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you is borne this day a Sauiour, which is Chriſt the Lord. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.10.</item>
                           <item>Behold, (at his yeelding vp of the ghoſt) the vaile of the Temple was rent in twaine, the earth ſhaked, ſtones were clouen, the graues opened, &amp;c. <hi>Math.</hi> 27.51.</item>
                           <item>Behold, (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) I come ſhortlie, &amp; my reward is with me to giue to euerie man as his worke ſhall be. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.12.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="102"/> Chriſt Ieſus came into the world:
<list>
                     <item>Not as a Iudge, but as a Phiſition.</item>
                     <item>Not as a deſtroyer, but as a Sauiour.</item>
                     <item>Not to call the iuſt, but ſinners to repentance.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="103"/> Chriſt Ieſus deſcended &amp; came (as was promiſed)
<list>
                     <item>Of the ſeede of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of the tribe of <hi>Iuda.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of the ſtock of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Beth-lehem</hi> brought him forth.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nazareth</hi> brought him vp.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Capernaum</hi> was his dwelling place.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Theoph.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:22"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="104"/> Chriſt Ieſus
<list>
                     <item>was transfigured vpon <hi>Mount Thabor.</hi> Matth. 17.1.</item>
                     <item>was crucified at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Heb. 13.12.</item>
                     <item>was taken into heauen at <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thania.</hi> Luk. 24.50.</item>
                  </list> He liues vpon the earth
<list>
                     <item>before his paſſion 33. yeres.</item>
                     <item>after his reſurrection. 40. daies <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="105"/> Chriſt Ieſus conſiſteth of three parts.
<list>
                     <item>Godhead,</item>
                     <item>Soule,</item>
                     <item>Bodie,</item>
                  </list> who
<list>
                     <item>as touching his humanitie had no father.</item>
                     <item>as concerning his diuinitie had no mother.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="106"/> It was neceſſarie that Chriſt ſhould die.
<list>
                     <item>That the Scriptures might be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.56.</item>
                     <item>That hee might bruſe the Serpents head. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</item>
                     <item>That wee might haue life through him. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.9.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="107"/> Chriſt is ſaid to die
<list>
                     <item>generallie,</item>
                     <item>ſpeciallie,</item>
                     <item>valiantlie,
<list>
                           <item>for all the world. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</item>
                           <item>for thoſe that beleeue. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12.</item>
                           <item>for that he ouercame death.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="108"/> Chriſt had ſmall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles when hee was taken priſoner, for
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iudas</hi> betraied him,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter</hi> forſware him.</item>
                     <item>Al the reſt forſook him.</item>
                  </list> And a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude followed him to his death:
<list>
                     <item>Some to hurt him.</item>
                     <item>Manie to mock him.</item>
                     <item>All to ſee the end of him.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="109"/> The benefite wee reape by the death of Chriſt is great.
<list>
                     <item>He reconciled vs to his father. <hi>Colo.</hi> 1.20. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.2.</item>
                     <item>He redeemed vs from the curſe of the lawe. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</item>
                     <item>He ſhewed vs an eaſier way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.30.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="110"/> Chriſt by his death became for man
<list>
                     <item>Curſe,</item>
                     <item>Sinne,</item>
                     <item>Seruile,</item>
                  </list> conſidering
<list>
                     <item>The qualitie of his death <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.23.</item>
                     <item>The integritie of his life. <hi>Eſau.</hi> 53.9.</item>
                     <item>The equalitie of his eſtate. <hi>Phi.</hi> 2</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:22"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="111"/> It was requiſite that Chriſt ſhould riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine after death.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe he foreſhewed it to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.9.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe his fleſh might not ſee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.31.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe we might bee iuſtified tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="112"/> It was neceſſarie that Chriſt ſhould aſcend af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was riſen.
<list>
                     <item>That he might be fullie glorified. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.39.</item>
                     <item>That hee might ſend downe the Comforter. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.7.</item>
                     <item>That he might become our Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.3.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="113"/> Chriſt ſaid that the Comforter at his comming ſhould reprooue the world of
<list>
                     <item>Sinne.</item>
                     <item>Righteouſnes:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe they beleeue not in him. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he is gone to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe the prince of this world is iudged. 10.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Iudgement.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſt hath ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vs a worthie and wonderfull good example, of
<list>
                     <item>Patience:</item>
                     <item>Humilitie:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="114"/> Becauſe being oppreſſed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, hee did not open his mouth, but was like a ſheepe dumme before the ſhearer. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.7.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he tooke vpon him the ſhape of a ſeruant being equall with his father. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he laid downe his own life for vs, than this what loue can be greater?</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Loue:</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="115"/> Chriſt is verie fitlie called, a
<list>
                     <item>Prieſt:</item>
                     <item>King:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe by his onelie ſacrifice hee appeaſed his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wrath.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he raigneth ouer all. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.22.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he declared his fathers will. <hi>Acts.</hi> 7.37.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prophet:</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:23"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="116"/> There be 3. things that beare record of Chriſt in heauen:
<list>
                     <item>the Father,</item>
                     <item>the Word,
<list>
                           <item>who ſent his Sonne.</item>
                           <item>which became fleſh.</item>
                           <item>which proceedes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>the Holie Ghoſt,</item>
                  </list> 2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 57.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="117"/> There be three things that beare witnes of Chriſt vpon earth.
<list>
                     <item>Spirit.</item>
                     <item>Water.</item>
                     <item>Bloud.</item>
                  </list> This aſſureth vs of our
<list>
                     <item>Adoption <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</item>
                     <item>Regeneration. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5.</item>
                     <item>Redemption. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="118"/> Thoſe that loue Chriſt, muſt
<list>
                     <item>followe after him:</item>
                     <item>paſſe through him:</item>
                     <item>drawe neere him.
<list>
                           <item>becauſe he is the truth.</item>
                           <item>becauſe he is the way.</item>
                           <item>becauſe he is the life.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="119"/> Chriſt being
<list>
                     <item>the truth,</item>
                     <item>the way,</item>
                     <item>the life,</item>
                  </list> manifeſteth to vs his <hi>Beza.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Nature:</item>
                     <item>Will:</item>
                     <item>Office:</item>
                  </list> So that in him we muſt
<list>
                     <item>begin.</item>
                     <item>continue.</item>
                     <item>ende.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="120"/> He that will come after Chriſt muſt
<list>
                     <item>denie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</item>
                     <item>take vp his Croſſe.</item>
                     <item>followe him.</item>
                  </list> wherin is laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs,
<list>
                     <item>Bondage,</item>
                     <item>Baſenes,
<list>
                           <item>In denying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</item>
                           <item>In taking vp the Croſſe.</item>
                           <item>In following Chriſt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hardnes,</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Barn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="121"/> Chriſt amaſed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed his enemies three manner of waies.
<list>
                     <item>By his ſound doctrine.</item>
                     <item>By his ſtrange miracles.</item>
                     <item>By his mild anſwers.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="122"/> Chriſt deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, as may appeare by theſe places. <hi>Articl. Relig.</hi> 3.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.17.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4 9.</item>
                  </list> For ſo wee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe in the Creede of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nicene.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Apoſtles.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="123"/> Many produce theſe direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to approue that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and not the ſoule of Chriſt deſcended.
<list>
                     <item>His ſpeach to the theefe vpon the Croſſe, <hi>this daie ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>His yeelding vp the ghoſt when he ſaid, <hi>It is finiſhed.</hi> Luke 23.43.</item>
                     <item>His agonie in the garden, in ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting drops of bloud &amp; water.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>For in hell is no redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> Luke 26.26.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:23"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="124"/> Chriſt ſpake moſt by para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to the multitude:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe by ſeeing, they ſhould ſee and not perceiue.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe by hearing, they ſhould heare and not vnderſtand.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it might be fulfilled which was ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.35.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.13.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="125"/> The great miracles and wonders Chriſt wrought in this world, were done partlie to this end:
<list>
                     <item>To ſhewe the great power, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and goodnes of his father. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.31.</item>
                     <item>To approue himſelfe the ſonne of God. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.22. And that he was ſent of him. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.42.</item>
                     <item>To confirme the authoritie and excellence of his doctrine, to winne the vnbeleeuers to it. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.23.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="126"/> Miracles are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten called in the Scriptures, <hi>Beza. Hebr.</hi> 2.4.
<list>
                     <item>Signes:</item>
                     <item>Wonders:
<list>
                           <item>Signes, becauſe they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare one thing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent another.</item>
                           <item>Wonders, becauſe they import ſome ſtrange &amp; vnaccuſtomable thing.</item>
                           <item>Vertues, becauſe they giue vs a glimſe of Gods power.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Vertues.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="127"/> Three ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites ſhewen to man by
<list>
                     <item>the Father,</item>
                     <item>the Sonne,</item>
                     <item>the Holie Ghoſt,
<list>
                           <item>He ſent his ſonne for our reconciliation.</item>
                           <item>His righteouſnes is ours by imputation.</item>
                           <item>This proceedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, for our ſanctification.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list> yet all one vnion.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:24"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="127"/> It is a ſinguler com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto vs to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the exceeding loue of Chriſt towards vs, by that
<list>
                     <item>he hath done:</item>
                     <item>he ſtill doth:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe he did not onelie ſacrifice himſelfe vpon the croſſe for our ſakes, but alſo ſatiſfied his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wrath for our ſins.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he did not onelie ſuffer for vs, but became alſo a continuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor for vs.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he hath not onlie ſaued vs, but ſhall alſo come to iudge vs.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>he will doo:</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="128"/> Such as will preſume of the time that Chriſt ſhall come to iudgement, may be reproued by theſe places.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 24.36.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.32.</item>
                     <item>1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5, 1.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>For it is not for vs to knowe the times and the ſeaſons the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath put in his owne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</hi> Acts 1.12.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="129"/> The comming of Chriſt is of 3. ſorts.
<list>
                     <item>Vnto men.</item>
                     <item>Into men.
<list>
                           <item>Vnto men, in the fleſh. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14.</item>
                           <item>Into men, by his ſpirit. <hi>Ioh</hi> 14.18.</item>
                           <item>Againſt men, in iudgement. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.12.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Againſt men.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="130"/> It ſtands vs not vpon ſo much to vſe diſputation of the time of Chriſtes comming to iudgement, as to be in a daylie preparation and reformation of our liues, conſidering
<list>
                     <item>Euerie mans end is imminent and vncertaine. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.14.</item>
                     <item>Euerie mans death is his latter daie. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.27.</item>
                     <item>Euerie man as he dieth ſhal be iudged. <hi>Eccle:</hi> 11.3.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="131"/> The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt to iudgement will be
<list>
                     <item>fearefull</item>
                     <item>ioyfull
<list>
                           <item>to the wicked;</item>
                           <item>to the godlie;
<list>
                                 <item>Becauſe that daie is to them the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their woe.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe it is to them the full fruition of their felicitie.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine alteration of all things.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>to both;</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>wonderfull</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:24"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="132"/> Theſe; things doo argue the world to drawe to an end.
<list>
                     <item>the Figtree:</item>
                     <item>charitie:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe it floriſheth. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.33.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe it waxeth cold. <hi>Ma.</hi> 24</item>
                           <item>Becauſe it aboundeth. <hi>Ma.</hi> 24</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>iniquitie:</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="133"/> The comming of Chriſt to iudgement will be of a ſodaine,
<list>
                     <item>As a woman trauailing with child.</item>
                     <item>As lightning from the Eaſt.</item>
                     <item>In the houre we thinke not.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Be ſober and watch: for hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are thoſe ſeruants, which the Lord when he commeth ſhal find waking.</hi> Luk 12.37</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="134"/> Although it was ſaid fifteene hundred, yeres &amp; more ſince, <hi>The day of the Lord is at hand,</hi> and yet the world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure: we muſt not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe words to be friuolous or fruſtrate: for thereby the Lord doth make manifeſt vnto vs
<list>
                     <item>his infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</item>
                     <item>his exceeding mercie
<list>
                           <item>in computation of yeares:</item>
                           <item>in delaying of the day.
<list>
                                 <item>Becauſe he doth not recko<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or record the time according to our knowledge or reaſon: for one day is with him as a thouſand yeres, and a thouſand yeres as one day. <hi>Pſal</hi> 90.4.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe hee would not haue vs periſh, but would all men to come to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe we doo not vſe the bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his patience &amp; long ſufferance accordingly <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.4</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration thereof.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>our impendent miſerie</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="135"/> We muſt yeeld ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt at the latter day of all our ſinnes committed in
<list>
                     <item>cogitation.</item>
                     <item>communication:</item>
                     <item>action.
<list>
                           <item>Our thoughts ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accuſe or excuſe vs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</item>
                           <item>Our words ſhall either iuſtifie or condemne vs. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.37.</item>
                           <item>Our workes ſhall then haue their due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.27.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:25"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="136"/> Our great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers at the yeelding vp of our laſt account ſhall be
<list>
                     <item>the lawe:</item>
                     <item>the diuell:</item>
                     <item>our conſcience:</item>
                  </list> beſides that
<list>
                     <item>We ſhall ſtand belples before ſo manie Iudges, as haue excelled vs in good works.</item>
                     <item>We ſhal be caſt by ſo many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidences, as haue giuen vs example of good life.</item>
                     <item>We ſhall bee conuinced with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> witneſſes, as haue admoniſhed vs with whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome counſell, and by their vertuous deedes, haue been patternes for vs to imitate.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="137"/> The Pope doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prefer, than make himſelfe equall, with the excellencie of our Sauiour Chriſt.
<list>
                     <item>He will bee the ſupreame of all the world, exempting himſelfe from al obedience to any earthly prince, or reuerence to any people when Chriſt was content to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the authoritie of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in paying toll, yea, euen to ſuch as were enemies to Religion. <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27.</item>
                     <item>He giueth out his feete to bee kiſſed of men, euen of Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, when Chriſt did neuer ſo lay foorth his feete, but that hee waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and wiped his poore Diſciples feete; and that becauſe they ſhould doo, as he had done to them. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.5, 15.</item>
                     <item>He doth of pitie free one, or other, euerie daie from the parties of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, when our Sauiour Chriſt did free none at all from thoſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh paines.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:25"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="138"/> The ſoule of man doth after death goe either to ioy or paine immediatlie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there bee three examples (beſides mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt proofes) that may flatlie refell the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious opinions of ſuch as falſlie affirme there is a Purgatorie.
<list>
                     <item>The ſoule of Lazarus recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into Abrahams bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.22.</item>
                     <item>The ſoule of the theefe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending into Paradiſe. <hi>Lu.</hi> 23.33.</item>
                     <item>The ſoule of the rich man deſcending into hel. <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.23.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="139"/> Theſe three things are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be continuallie noted;
<list>
                     <item>The ſecrets of God are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable.</item>
                     <item>The ioyes of heauen are vnſpeakable.</item>
                     <item>The paines of hell are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="140"/> A vertuous man diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his waie in this world
<list>
                     <item>Prudentlie,</item>
                     <item>Penitentlie,</item>
                     <item>Prouident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
<list>
                           <item>To diſpoſe and order things preſent.</item>
                           <item>To conſider his miſdeedes paſt.</item>
                           <item>To prouide and forſee for things to come.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>S Paul diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; parts.
<list>
                     <item>Spirit.</item>
                     <item>Soule.</item>
                     <item>Bodie.</item>
                  </list> for then is man fullie ſanctified,
<list>
                     <item>when his minde thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth nothing</item>
                     <item>when his will couets nothing.</item>
                     <item>when his bodie exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes nothing.</item>
                  </list> contrarie to the will of GOD. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="141"/> A godlie Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to liue in this world <hi>Barnard.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Soberlie.</item>
                     <item>Iuſtlie.</item>
                     <item>Godlie.
<list>
                           <item>concerning himſelfe,</item>
                           <item>concerning his neighbour.</item>
                           <item>concerning God.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="142"/> That he keep his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die temperatly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abuſing the gifts of God wantonlie or waſtfullie.</item>
                                 <item>That he deale plainly, vprightly, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie, without diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</item>
                                 <item>That he preſume not too much of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but referre all to Gods good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; prouidence.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:26"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="143"/> A man ſhould not doo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>If forgetfulnes confound not his memorie.</item>
                     <item>If error obſcure not his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</item>
                     <item>If iniquitie depraue not his will.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="144"/> The ſtate of man is three waies to bee conſidered.
<list>
                     <item>by creation</item>
                     <item>by fall and ſinne</item>
                     <item>by regeneration
<list>
                           <item>he was made like to the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, which i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is expounded here <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24.</item>
                           <item>he became ſlaue vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, &amp; ſo procured the ſame thraldome to al po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities.</item>
                           <item>he is ingrafted into chriſt by faith, and in him hath recouered his former right.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="145"/> A man is happie in this world that can
<list>
                     <item>Reioyce in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</item>
                     <item>Beare all croſſes pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientlie.</item>
                     <item>Lament his ſinne ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfullie.</item>
                  </list> following the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of
<list>
                     <item>Paul. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</item>
                     <item>Iob. 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>Peter. <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.62.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="146"/> Euerie man ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies bee mindfull of his
<list>
                     <item>Creation:</item>
                     <item>Conuerſation:</item>
                     <item>Diſſolution:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe he is duſt, &amp; to duſt he ſhall returne. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe hee muſt one daie yeeld accompt of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12.24.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe his end is vncertain; and as he falles, ſuch iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment followes. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.3.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:26"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="147"/> Herein conſiſts the whole duetie of man towards God.
<list>
                     <item>To feare him</item>
                     <item>To loue him</item>
                     <item>To keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements
<list>
                           <item>for his iuſtice:</item>
                           <item>for his goodnes:</item>
                           <item>to confirme it.
<list>
                                 <item>Becauſe it is horrible to fall into his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe hee loued vs firſt. 1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 4.19.</item>
                                 <item>Becauſe thoſe that loue him will keepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements. 2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.3.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="148"/> S. <hi>Iames</hi> willeth euerie man to be
<list>
                     <item>Swift to heare.</item>
                     <item>Slowe to ſpeake.</item>
                     <item>Slowe to wrath.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 1.19.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="149"/> No man hath cauſe to glorie in himſelf, if hee conſider what he is, of himſelfe,
<list>
                     <item>By Subſtance,</item>
                     <item>By Nature,</item>
                     <item>By Knowledge,
<list>
                           <item>he was made of the duſt. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.7.</item>
                           <item>he is the childe of wrath. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.3.</item>
                           <item>he is but a beaſt. <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.14.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="150"/> For a man to glorie or attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute anie praiſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in anie good attempts it is
<list>
                     <item>Vanitie:</item>
                     <item>Arrogancie:</item>
                     <item>Iniquitie:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe of himſelfe he cannot think a good thought, much leſſe doo a good deed, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he attributeth that to himſelfe which is proper to GOD: for euerie good and perfect gift commeth from aboue. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he doth not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the giuer thankfullie: for all praiſe and glorie is to be giuen to God. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Herod</hi> by abridging God of his glory came to a moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable end. <hi>Acts.</hi> 12.23.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:27"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="151"/> This may abate the hie aſpiring mind of man.
<list>
                     <item>His birth being ſinfull. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.9</item>
                     <item>His life being miſerable. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.9</item>
                     <item>His body being worms meat. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.9</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="152"/> Euerie man muſt haue a godlie care to liue in this world.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe GOD hath commanded he ſhould labour ſixe daies. <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.9.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe he is worſe than an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell that prouideth not for his houſhold. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe he may auoid the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience of idlenes. 2. <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 3.10. which bringeth much euill. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 12.11.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="153"/> A good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to be
<list>
                     <item>Wiſe.</item>
                     <item>Simple.</item>
                     <item>Fooliſh.
<list>
                           <item>wiſe, vnto that which is good. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.19.</item>
                           <item>ſimple, concerning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.19.</item>
                           <item>fooliſh, in reſpect of this world. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="154"/> Heretickes and erronious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are verie dangerous to be permitted amongſt godlie chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, conſidering
<list>
                     <item>Their condition:</item>
                     <item>Their corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</item>
                     <item>The ſeaſon:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe they thinke it not enough to erre and doo euill themſelues, except they drawe others with them, as appeareth in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.10. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 14.21.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance they will defile manie. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.15. For a little leauen leaueneth the whole lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe in theſe latter times many ſhall giue heede to Spirits of errour, and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of diuels. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:27"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="155"/> Wicked men are verie fitlie compared in the Scriptures
<list>
                     <item>to thornes;</item>
                     <item>to chaffe;</item>
                     <item>to tares;
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe they be as prickes to procure hurt to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe as the winde doth ſcatter the chaffe, ſo ſhall they be ſoone cut off from the face of the earth.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe as tares are to bee bound in bundels &amp; burnt, ſo ſhall they be in hell fire.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="156"/> Wicked men are called by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie names, and compared in the Scriptures
<list>
                     <item>to Foxes;</item>
                     <item>to Dogges;</item>
                     <item>to beaſtes;
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe they are ſubtill in vndermining, &amp; doing of miſchiefe: in ſo much as the Church requireth to haue the foxes take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaie. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe they are curriſh in controlling, and barking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all goodnes. Hereof <hi>Paule</hi> willeth the <hi>Phillip.</hi> to beware of dogges. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.2</item>
                           <item>Becauſe they are prophane in their liues, and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their kinde worſe than beaſts. So <hi>Paule</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth that hee fought with beaſtes at <hi>Epheſus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of men. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="157"/> The wicked and vngodlie are not to be
<list>
                     <item>Supported purpoſelie:</item>
                     <item>Accompanied willinglie:</item>
                     <item>Condemned vtterlie:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe it is abomination before God to iuſtifie the wicked. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 17.15.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe it is dangerous, for hee that toucheth pitch ſhall be defiled. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 13.1.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe the Lord wil haue mercie on whom he will, and when he pleaſe. <hi>Rom</hi> 9.15.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:28"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="158"/> Theſe ſayings maie terrifie ſuch as attempt any euill.
<list>
                     <item>The face of the Lord is againſt him. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12.</item>
                     <item>Tribulation and anguiſh ſhall be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his ſoule. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.9.</item>
                     <item>There ſhall be no ende of plagues to him. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 24.20.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="159"/> God tempteth no man to euill, but we are drawne to it
<list>
                     <item>By the diuell, who watcheth to worke our ouerthrowe.</item>
                     <item>By our owne concupiſcence to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his ſuggeſtions.</item>
                     <item>By vicious companie and ill perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of others when we be ſeduced.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="160"/> The Diuell will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine vs in our muſings, if we take not great heed, for in them <hi>Barn.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>He talketh with vs wittilie.</item>
                     <item>He eggeth vs cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninglie.</item>
                     <item>Hee deceiueth vs craftelie.</item>
                  </list> whom if we reſiſt by faith, the Lord will
<list>
                     <item>Ouerlook vs figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</item>
                     <item>Succour vs fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</item>
                     <item>Crowne vs ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="161"/> The Diuells haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge after a ſort: for
<list>
                     <item>They beleeue there is a God, and feare and tremble. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.19.</item>
                     <item>They can pleade Scripture for their owne purpoſe. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.6.</item>
                     <item>They acknowledge Chriſtes comming to iudgement. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.29.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="162"/> The Diuell hath three euill proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he is
<list>
                     <item>Subtill</item>
                     <item>Strong</item>
                     <item>Cruell
<list>
                           <item>as a Serpent:</item>
                           <item>as a Lyon:</item>
                           <item>as a Tiger:
<list>
                                 <item>For hee can transforme himſelfe into many ſhapes (yea into an Angell of light) and vſe manie ſhifts to deceiue withall.</item>
                                 <item>For hee is not ſo buſie in ſeeking daylie for his pray, as he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible to reſiſt where he aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</item>
                                 <item>For where hee hath any enterance at all, he will neuer reſt vntill he bringeth to confuſion.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:28"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="163"/> The Diuell vſed three polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to tempt Chriſt in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, perſwading him
<list>
                     <item>To diſtruſt in God.</item>
                     <item>To the deſire of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and honor.</item>
                     <item>To a vain co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence of himſelfe.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Beza. Mat.</hi> 20.</item>
               <item>Wee haue 3. cruell foes that fight againſt the ſpirit in this life, the
<list>
                     <item>Fleſh.</item>
                     <item>World.</item>
                     <item>Diuell.</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="164"/> The fierceſt foe in this fight is the Diuell: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee may expell with theſe three weapons.
<list>
                     <item>Faith.</item>
                     <item>Praier.</item>
                     <item>the word of God.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="165"/> We ought not to followe the luſtes of the fleſh, but leade our liues holilie. <hi>Beza.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe thoſe luſts although they flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vs, yet they ceaſe not to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſaluation. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe we are citizens in heauen, and therefore ought to leade our liues thereafter, although we be ſtrangers here.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe the glorie of God is greatlie ſet foorth by that meanes, whileſt by example of our honeſt life, euen the moſt prophane men are brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and ſubmit themſelues vnto him.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="166"/> There are many walk in this world, (ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi>) <hi>Phil</hi> 3.19.
<list>
                     <item>Whoſe God is their bellie.</item>
                     <item>Whoſe glorie is their ſhame.</item>
                     <item>Whoſe end is damnation.</item>
                  </list> The whole world lieth in wickednes 2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.19.</item>
               <item>The wretchednes of this world, made
<list>
                     <item>Salomon ſay</item>
                     <item>Iob ſay</item>
                     <item>Paule ſay
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="167"/> The day of death is better than the day one is borne. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7 3.</item>
                           <item>My ſoule is cut off though I liue. <hi>Iob.</hi> 10.1.</item>
                           <item>I deſire to bee looſed from this life. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:29"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="168"/> What ſhould we ſo accompt of this world, ſeeing
<list>
                     <item>The faſhion of it goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31.</item>
                     <item>The wiſedome of it is mere fooliſhnes. <hi>Iob.</hi> 37</item>
                     <item>The amitie of it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie with God. <hi>Ia.</hi> 4.4</item>
                  </list> Vſe this world as though you vſed it not, ſaith <hi>Paule?</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="169"/> Theſe 3 things may withdrawe a man from deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring long life in this world.
<list>
                     <item>The wretchednes of his life.</item>
                     <item>The grieuouſnes of his ſinnes.</item>
                     <item>The greatnes of his accompt.
<list>
                           <item>becauſe it is but a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual temptation and full of miſerie.</item>
                           <item>becauſe they will more increaſe by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance.</item>
                           <item>becauſe it wilbe the more fearefull at the yeelding vp.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="170"/> The godlie deſire to be out of this world:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe it is variable and nothing but vanitie.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe of the innumerable euills they are ſubiect to.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe they long to be cloathed with the heauenlie habit.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="171"/> Life is verie ſweete, and ſo ſweete, that it hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the godlie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the ſafetie of it, by ſhifts.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauid</hi> doubting of euill dealing, fained himſelfe mad to ſaue his life. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.13.14.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Paule</hi> perceiuing their crueltie that would kill him, had rather in the night bee let downe in a basket, than abide. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.25.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter</hi> fearing death, did forſweare his maſter. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18.27.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="172"/> The faithfull and godlie in this world doo dailie
<list>
                     <item>Fight,</item>
                     <item>Faint,</item>
                     <item>Fall,</item>
                  </list> by reaſon of their
<list>
                     <item>Aduerſarie.</item>
                     <item>Infidelitie.</item>
                     <item>Infirmitie.</item>
                  </list> Yet they ſhall not be caſt away. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.24.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="173"/> Theſe 3. things are worthie to be conſidered.
<list>
                     <item>He that liueth beſt doth dailie ſinne.</item>
                     <item>He is happie that hath grace to repent.</item>
                     <item>He is bleſſed to whom God imputeth no ſin.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:29"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="174"/> Although euery man is a ſinner, yet euerie ſinne is not of like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: for ſome ſinne
<list>
                     <item>of Ignorance,</item>
                     <item>of Infirmitie,</item>
                     <item>of Malice,
<list>
                           <item>as <hi>Paule</hi> did. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</item>
                           <item>as <hi>Dauid</hi> did. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2. &amp;c.</item>
                           <item>as <hi>Nebuchad-nezzer</hi> did. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.1.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Euerie ſinner muſt beware of theſe three things, of
<list>
                     <item>procraſtination,</item>
                     <item>preſumption,</item>
                     <item>prouocation,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="175"/> In delaying the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.50</item>
                           <item>In ſinning ſtill vpon hope. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.</item>
                           <item>In ſinning obſtinatlie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holie Ghoſt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Sinne is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, but
<list>
                     <item>A ſweet poyſon.</item>
                     <item>A flattering death.</item>
                     <item>A deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſoule.</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="176"/> wherof there be two ſorts.
<list>
                     <item>Original.</item>
                     <item>Actuall.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Adam did further his fall, and increaſe his ſinne in the gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den three waies.
<list>
                     <item>By ambition,</item>
                     <item>By hypocriſie,</item>
                     <item>By impenitencie,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="177"/> becauſe he thought to be as God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good from euill <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6.</item>
                           <item>becauſe hee hid the cauſe of his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which was the breach of Gods commandements. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10.</item>
                           <item>becauſe hee was ſo farre from acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his tranſgreſſion, that he bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened God with his fault, in that hee had giuen him a wife. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.12.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>It appeareth by this that ſinne is
<list>
                     <item>Excerable,</item>
                     <item>Deteſtable,</item>
                     <item>Intollerable,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="178"/> becauſe it repented the Lord that he had made man on the earth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6.</item>
                           <item>becauſe hee deſtroyeth dumme creatures for our cauſe. <hi>Zephan.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</item>
                           <item>becauſe hee would not ſpare his onelie ſonne for our ſinnes.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:30"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="179"/> It is an exceeding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to a Sinner, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<list>
                     <item>That God is as well a father as a Lord.</item>
                     <item>That Chriſt is as well a Sauiour as a Iudge</item>
                     <item>That the Scripture include as well a Goſpell as a Law.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="180"/> Sinners ſhould not diſpaire of Gods mercie, if they did but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which apea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto them
<list>
                     <item>By his readines in calling,</item>
                     <item>By his worthines in ſparing,</item>
                     <item>By his vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in ſtriking,
<list>
                           <item>before they crie (ſaith the Lord) I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, and whileſt they are yet think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to ſpeake I will heare. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.24.</item>
                           <item>he maketh as though he ſawe not the ſins of men, becauſe they ſhould amend. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 11.20.</item>
                           <item>he taketh no pleaſure in the deſtruction, but in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion of ſinners. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.23.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="181"/> What greater comfort can ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners haue, ſith Chriſt himſelfe ſaith,
<list>
                     <item>Aske and ye ſhall haue.</item>
                     <item>Seeke and ye ſhall finde.</item>
                     <item>Knock &amp; it ſhalbe opened vnto you.</item>
                  </list> I ſtande at the dore &amp; knock, &amp;c. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.20.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="182"/> He that wil ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mercie by true repentance,
<list>
                     <item>Muſt acknowledge his ſinnes ſorowful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with the prodigall ſonne.</item>
                     <item>Muſt ſhewe a heartie contrition for the ſame, and loath them.</item>
                     <item>Muſt do good workes worthie amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment afterward. <hi>Asts.</hi> 26.20.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:30"/>
               <item>He that is fullie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſinnes, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member theſe three things.
<list>
                     <item>the mercie of God.</item>
                     <item>the ſubtiltie of Sathan.</item>
                     <item>the frailtie of himſelfe.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="183"/> That he be thankfull vnto him, for his gratious goodneſſe ſhewen vnto him, by remitting his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, &amp; receiuing him into his fauor.</item>
                           <item>That hee watch and praie continuallie, for the diuell goeth about like a roaring Lyon ſeeking who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee maie deuoure. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</item>
                           <item>That ſeeing his own infirmities hee may the rather depende vpon God, &amp; craue his mercie to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his faith and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or els he ſhal not be able to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the oppoſite euills, he is ſubiect to.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>God ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to all his people.
<list>
                     <item>Merciful</item>
                     <item>Good</item>
                     <item>Iuſt
<list>
                           <item>to the elect,</item>
                           <item>to the reprobat,</item>
                           <item>to both of them
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="184"/> In pardoning their ſinnes.</item>
                                 <item>Albeit they cannot feele the ſweete comfort of the ſame.</item>
                                 <item>In giuing iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:31"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="185"/> The Lord wil not reiect the ſuite of a Sinner, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accept of it, vnleſſe in asking, hee hath a ſpecial regard of theſe three things.
<list>
                     <item>Of the time.</item>
                     <item>Of the manner.</item>
                     <item>Of the end.
<list>
                           <item>For the Lord will not bee found at all times, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth oportunitie. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of faith the Prophet <hi>Eſai,</hi> ſeeke the Lord while hee may be found, &amp; cal vpon him while he is nere <hi>Eſai.</hi> 55.6. The fiue fooliſh vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming too late were excluded. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.12.</item>
                           <item>For the Lord will not onlie haue ſuch as call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him depart from iniquitie, but wil alſo haue their praiers proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the verie hart. Then ſhalt thou call (ſaith the ſame Prophet to the hypocrites) and the Lord ſhall anſwere, thou ſhalt crie and he ſhall ſay, here I am. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 58.9.</item>
                           <item>For God requireth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly importunitie of vs in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; as appeareth by the woman of <hi>Canaan. Matth.</hi> 15.28. but alſo reſpecteth the end of our requeſtes, in asking according to his will, otherwiſe wee maie aske and receiue not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee aske amiſſe to conſume it on our luſtes. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.3.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:31"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="186"/> Hee that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime a ſinner muſt obſerue three things in handling of him, which the Apoſtle S. Peter practiſed with the Iewes. <hi>Acts.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15, 17, 29.
<list>
                     <item>Demonſtration of the matter.</item>
                     <item>Reprehenſion of the offence.</item>
                     <item>Exhortation to the ſinner.
<list>
                           <item>In ſhewing him (by the word of God) it is a ſinne, that it may ſo appeare vnto him: whereby he may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acknowledge it before God.</item>
                           <item>In reproouing him (by the iudgements of GOD pronounced againſt the ſame) that hee may both heare the puniſhment he hath worthelie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and alſo thereby be the more terrified from attempting euill.</item>
                           <item>In perſwading him (by the promiſes of Gods mercie) that he may not onelie bee driuen from diſpaire, but alſo by that meanes bee drawne to amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="187"/> The ſame notable example of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in his conuerſion, doth miniſter ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler matter to euerie Sinner, wherein he may note three ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cauſes for his comfort.
<list>
                     <item>1. That GOD will puniſh the wicked that he intendeth to ſaue: that by this meanes they may ſeeke him by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, according to that ſame ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Pſalmiſt. <hi>When he ſlew them, they ſought him, and returned and ſought God earlie.</hi> Pſal. 78.34.</item>
                     <item>2. That the mercie of GOD is verie great, who although he will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſinne to paſſe vnpuniſhed, yet hee is readie to forgiue, though it be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie grieuous, as he hath promiſed by the Prophet <hi>Eſaias</hi> to ſuch as heartilie repent. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 5.7, 8, 9.</item>
                     <item>3. That thoſe whom GOD hath thus called, are not to returne to their ſinnes, as the dogge to his vomite, but as becommeth newe borne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to liue in holines and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes all the daies of their life. <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.75.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:32"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="188"/> The manifold examples in the Scriptures of the falling and riſing of the godlie, were done of God (amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) to this end,
<list>
                     <item>For the glorie of himſelfe:</item>
                     <item>For the good of them:</item>
                     <item>For the profite of others:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe he will haue his power knowne to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile aboue his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that it is hee that can make them riſe and fall at his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he wil haue their owne imperfections &amp; infirmities appeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, what they are of them-ſelues, if hee doth faile them but a little, to the ende they ſhould not preſume of themſelues, but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther depend vppon his prouidence and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe ſuch as bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt drowned in the deapth of their ſinnes, ſhould not fall into deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the verie elect haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded moſt horriblie, but that they ſhould bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged therby to call for grace: ſeeing his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is not yet ſhortned, but that he can helpe others as hee did thoſe. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 59.1.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:32"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="189"/> Euerie particuler ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is not ſufficient to prooue or eſtabliſh a generall doctrine, for then wee might beleeue 3. things lawfull, which are not to be allowed.
<list>
                     <item>That women might miniſter the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, becauſe <hi>Zipporah</hi> did circumciſe her ſonne <hi>Exod.</hi> 4 25.</item>
                     <item>That wee ought to praie for the dead, becauſe <hi>Iudas</hi> did ſo 2. <hi>Mac.</hi> 12.44.</item>
                     <item>That wee may deſperatlie kill our ſelues, becauſe <hi>Razis</hi> did ſo (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the author of the <hi>Maccha.</hi> much commendeth.) 2. <hi>Maccha.</hi> 14.41.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="190"/> God ſometimes ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſeruants, yea the moſt godlie, to bee vexed with Sathan.
<list>
                     <item>That they ſhould not be puffed vp with any preſumption of themſelues.</item>
                     <item>That they may be made perfect by that continuall exerciſe. 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 12.9.</item>
                     <item>That they ought the more earneſtlie to be inſtant in praier.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="191"/> God trieth his children many waies in this world, ſometimes
<list>
                     <item>By proſperitie,</item>
                     <item>By pouertie,</item>
                     <item>By perſecution
<list>
                           <item>To ſee if they will repoſe more felicitie in their goodes, than in him that gaue them, as he did by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              </hi> in offering his ſonne. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.1.2.</item>
                           <item>To ſee if they wil not as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientlie depart from their goods, as he was willing to beſtow them: as he did by <hi>Iob,</hi> by taking away all he had. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</item>
                           <item>To ſee if they will rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie him, than die in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: as hee did by manie Prophets, Apoſtles, and godlie Martirs.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:33"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="192"/> God keepeth his children common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this world ſparinglie.
<list>
                     <item>That they may not be too proud with proſperitie.</item>
                     <item>That by this meanes they may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fee their owne miſerie.</item>
                     <item>That thereby they may the rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on his mercie.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="193"/> The godlie think that day ill ſpent, wherein they
<list>
                     <item>Do nothing</item>
                     <item>Say nothing</item>
                     <item>Think nothing</item>
                  </list> that may make
<list>
                     <item>To the glorie of God.</item>
                     <item>To the comfort of themſelues.</item>
                     <item>To the edifying of others.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="194"/> Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are to the godlie and faithfull
<list>
                     <item>a Confirmation of Gods loue.</item>
                     <item>a Probatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their faith &amp; patience.</item>
                     <item>a Purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their liues:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe he will not ſuffer them to bee condemned with the world, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee chaſtiſeth thoſe he loueth. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.17.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe he will ſee if they will ſtand as ſtrict to him now, as they promiſed in proſperitie; not that God is ignorant of the iſſue, but becauſe hee would haue it appeare to others, that he doth crown ſuch with his glorie as conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue conſtant. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.13.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe hee vſeth theſe croſſes to make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber their miſerable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, that by theſe meanes they may bee made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect againſt the daie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:33"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="195"/> The godlie do reioyce in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3.
<list>
                     <item>Tribulation bringeth forth patience.</item>
                     <item>Patience, experience:</item>
                     <item>Experience, hope:</item>
                  </list> and hope maketh not aſhamed.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="196"/> The afflictions of the godlie dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: <hi>Beza.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe the godlie communicate with Chriſt in their afflictions, and therfore ſhall in time alſo be partakers of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe in ſuffering theſe croſſes, their adoption is ſealed in them by the ſpirit of GOD, although the infidels thinke farre otherwiſe, who in afflicting the godlie blaſpheme God.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe they are not afflicted for their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill doings, but for righteouſnes ſake, which miniſtreth vnſpeakable ioye to them.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="197"/> The faithfull in their afflictions haue this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God.
<list>
                     <item>That hee will lay no more vppon them than he will make them able to beare. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</item>
                     <item>That hee will deliuer them out of their troubles in a good time.</item>
                     <item>That hee will giue them a Crowne of life in the end. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.10.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="198"/> Such as ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction may take comfort by the conſideration of theſe ſayings.
<list>
                     <item>Wee muſt by manie afflictions enter the kingdome of heauen. <hi>Acts.</hi> 14.22.</item>
                     <item>All that liue godlie in Chriſt ſhall ſuffer perſecution. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</item>
                     <item>All the afflictions in this life are not counted worthie the glorie of the life to come. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:34"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="199"/> Afflictions are verie neceſſarie for the godlie, <hi>Beza. Iam.</hi> 1.3.4
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe their faith is tried through afflictions, which ought to be moſt pure, for ſo it is behouable for them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>Becauſe patience a farre paſſing &amp; more excellent vertue is by this meanes ingendred in them.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe the Croſſe is as it were the inſtrument wherwith God doth poliſh and fine them: therefore the worke and effect of afflictions, is the perfecting of them in Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="200"/> Patience is very expedient for Chriſtians:
<list>
                     <item>That by it their faith may bee confirmed. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5.</item>
                     <item>That thereby they may be made perfect and entire. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.4.</item>
                     <item>That after they haue done the will of God, they might receiue the promiſe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="201"/> There be three wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie examples of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſet forth vnto vs. The example
<list>
                     <item>of Chriſt himſelfe, the onelie pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of patience.</item>
                     <item>of Iob, whoſe patience yee haue heard of. <hi>Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 5 10.</item>
                     <item>of the Prophets, whoſe patient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples appeare vnto vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="202"/> Theſe 3. points are required of the faithfull.
<list>
                     <item>That their talke be godlie.</item>
                     <item>That Gods law be in their hart.</item>
                     <item>That their life be vpright.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.30.31. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="203"/> There be three things very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for the godlie.
<list>
                     <item>Proſperitie
<list>
                           <item>of themſelues:</item>
                           <item>of the wicked:</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Extremitie of affliction:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe it maketh them to forget God. Hereof, ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> I ſaid in my proſperitie I ſhould not bee moued. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe it maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſpute with God, thinking he doth not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conſider of them: as the ſame Prophet did. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.13.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe it maketh them diſpaire of God, thinking bee would deſtroye them vtterlie. In ſo much as the ſame Pſalmiſt burſt foorth with theſe ſayings. Stay thine anger fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, that I may recouer my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth before I goe hence, and bee not. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.13.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:34"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cornelius</hi> was called a deuout man in 3. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.2
<list>
                     <item>He feared God, with al his houſhold.</item>
                     <item>He gaue much almes to the people</item>
                     <item>He praied to God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie.</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="204"/> And <hi>Iob</hi> a iuſt man likewiſe in 3. reſpects.
<list>
                     <item>He feared God. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>He eſchewed euil <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>Hee did good workes. <hi>Iob.</hi> 31.16.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="205"/> He that will be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, muſt be
<list>
                     <item>Iuſt in word.</item>
                     <item>Vpright in deed.</item>
                     <item>Vndefiled in thought.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Barnard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="206"/> The iuſt do reioyce at the puniſhment of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe therby God ſheweth himſelfe Iudge of the world, and by this meanes continueth his honor and glorie. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.2.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe hereby he ſheweth he hath care ouer his children, in that hee puniſheth their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.11.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe by their example others may feare, and be reformed, in ſome meaſure. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.13.2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="207"/> We ought to loue and do good, to our enemies.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe Chriſt himſelfe did ſo; whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample we ought to imitate. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.24.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it is not praiſe worthie, to loue where we are beloued; for ſo doo the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and publicans. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.46.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it is our duetie not onelie to ſuffer iniurie, but alſo to do good <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.17.20.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="208"/> Such as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in malice and hatred, ſhould conſider
<list>
                     <item>Their praiers are vnprofitable, if they aske mercie and forgiue not <hi>Mark.</hi> 11.25.</item>
                     <item>The Lords Supper is prophaned, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it vnworthelie. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.</item>
                     <item>They themſelues are but manſlaiers, if they liue not in charitie. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.13, 15.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="209"/> Theſe three things (ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Syracke</hi>) my ſoule loueth.
<list>
                     <item>Vnitie of brethren.</item>
                     <item>Loue of neighbours.</item>
                     <item>Agreement of man and wife.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Eccle</hi> 25.1.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:35"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="210"/> Euerie one ought to knowe how farre, and in what manner he ought to loue
<list>
                     <item>A mutual friend,</item>
                     <item>A malitious foe,</item>
                     <item>A manifeſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<list>
                           <item>in God:</item>
                           <item>for the loue of God:</item>
                           <item>for humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſake.
<list>
                                 <item>becauſe in louing otherwiſe he ſhall offend GOD: for hee that loueth father or mother, (much leſſe a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon friend) more than me (ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt) is not worthie of me. <hi>Matth</hi> 10.37.</item>
                                 <item>becauſe hee cannot loue God whom he hath not ſeene, if hee loueth not his brother that he hath ſeene. 2. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.20.</item>
                                 <item>becauſe wee ought to haue a conſideration of his ſoule, though wee haue a deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſinnes: according to the counſell of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who willeth vs to count ſuch a one, not as an enemie, but admoniſh him as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.15.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="211"/> There be three things prohibited, which ought not to be vſed of anie, to their verie ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.
<list>
                     <item>To enuie their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate:</item>
                     <item>To reioyce at their fall:</item>
                     <item>To render euill for euill:
<list>
                           <item>becauſe enuie turneth to a mans owne euill in the ende, according as it is written, no enuious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or ſuch like ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heauen. <hi>Gala.</hi> 5.21.</item>
                           <item>becauſe it is dangerous, leſt the Lord ſee it (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) &amp; it diſpleaſe him, and hee turne his wrath from him, to be auenged on thee. <hi>Prouer</hi> 24.18.</item>
                           <item>becauſe it is the part of a good Chriſtian, not to vſe the meanes to further a miſchiefe, but to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come euil with good. <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.20.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:35"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="212"/> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> being both a Prince and a Prophet, ſheweth wherein a Kings charge ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth.
<list>
                     <item>To prouide faithfullie for his people.</item>
                     <item>To guide them by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</item>
                     <item>To defend them by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.72. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="213"/> Such as are called to be Rulers and Magiſtrates ought to be
<list>
                     <item>Men of courage, fearing God. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21.</item>
                     <item>Men dealing truelie, hating couetouſnes. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21.</item>
                     <item>Men of wiſedome, and vnderſtanding <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> 1.13.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="214"/> Such as intend euill attempts, or vſe any rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious meanes or miſchief againſt Gods annointed, Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; ſhould reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the end of theſe 3. examples.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing but priuily cut off the lappe of King <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, was touched ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementlie in heart for it 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5, 6.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Abſalom</hi> hauing betraied King <hi>Dauid</hi> his father, came to an vntimely death, for he was hanged by the haire of his head vpon an Oke. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.14.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Achitophel</hi> being a Coadiutor, in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the lewd practiſes of <hi>Abſalom</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his father; when hee perceiued his counſell preuailed not, he went deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratlie and hong himſelfe. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.23.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="215"/> He that will vſe reuerent obedience to his Prince, muſt be verie carefull to conſider, how dangerous it is to offend
<list>
                     <item>in thinking euill:</item>
                     <item>in vttering euill:</item>
                     <item>in committing euill:
<list>
                           <item>for the ſoule of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal carrie the voyce, and that which hath winges ſhall declare the matter. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 10.20.</item>
                           <item>for it is written, Thou ſhalt not ſpeake euill of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of thy people. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28.</item>
                           <item>for if the Lord doth deteſt the euill intent, and forbid filthie ſpeaches, how much more doth he abhorre the act of euill, and wil puniſh the malefactors.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:36"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="216"/> There be 3. points commendable and neceſſarie for him that is in authoritie.
<list>
                     <item>To haue the fauour of the people.</item>
                     <item>To procure their wealth.</item>
                     <item>To bee gentle and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing toward them.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Eſter.</hi> 10.3. &amp;c</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="217"/> Good and godlie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ought to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed in reſpect of
<list>
                     <item>Conſcience:</item>
                     <item>Feare:</item>
                     <item>Neceſſitie:
<list>
                           <item>Becauſe they are ordained of GOD: whoſe will is, they ſhould be obeyed. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe they are his miniſters, to take vengeance on all that do euill. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 4.</item>
                           <item>Becauſe where no rule is, all things goe to ruine <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.6.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="218"/> Herein conſiſts the whole duetie of Magiſtrates.
<list>
                     <item>To defend and preſerue the godlie. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</item>
                     <item>To bridle and puniſh the wicked. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</item>
                     <item>To iudge righteouſlie betweene both. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.18.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="219"/> Magiſtrates ought conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<list>
                     <item>That the higher they are placed, the ſorer is their triall. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 6.8.</item>
                     <item>That their negligence in ſuffering euill is their iniquitie.</item>
                     <item>That the ill example of themſelues is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinne.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="220"/> There be three things not tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in anie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.
<list>
                     <item>Partialitie</item>
                     <item>Crueltie</item>
                     <item>Briberie
<list>
                           <item>in reſpecting perſons:</item>
                           <item>in miniſtring iuſtice:</item>
                           <item>in detayning right:
<list>
                                 <item>for that is abomination in the ſight of GOD. <hi>Leu.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17.</item>
                                 <item>for ſuch meaſure as they mete, ſhalbe met to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.24.</item>
                                 <item>for fire ſhall conſume the houſes of bribes <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="221"/> Hee that will bee maſter ouer a godlie houſhold, muſt knowe his owne duetie to his familie, as
<list>
                     <item>Wife.</item>
                     <item>Children.</item>
                     <item>Seruants</item>
                  </list> and how to vſe them being
<list>
                     <item>well diſpoſed.</item>
                     <item>euill inclined.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:36"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="222"/> The duetie of the houſholder, is
<list>
                     <item>To knowe the ſtate of his flocke. <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.23.</item>
                     <item>To inſtruct them in the feare of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5.</item>
                     <item>To prouide carefullie for his familie. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="223"/> The husband ought to haue a ſpeciall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt care and loue to his wife in 3. reſpects:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe ſhe commeth of his owne fleſh: and therefore, who will bee bitter to his owne bodie.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe they are the weaker veſſels, and therefore who will not beare with their infirmities.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe ſhe was made as a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to man. &amp; therfore he is worſe than a beaſt that wilbe cruel to her.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="224"/> There be three cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould mooue and make the wife obey, honor, and ſubmit her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe to her husband.
<list>
                     <item>The prioritie of mans creation.</item>
                     <item>The ſuperioritie of his placing.</item>
                     <item>The iniquitie, of the womans procuring.
<list>
                           <item>becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> was firſt formed, then <hi>Eue</hi> afterwarde for his ſake. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13.</item>
                           <item>becauſe man was made to beare rule: whereunto <hi>Paule</hi> verie well alludeth and ſaith: that as Chriſt is the head of the Church, ſo is the man of the woman. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.23.</item>
                           <item>becauſe the man was deceiued by the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherevpon God enioyned her, (amongſt other) this puniſhment of ſubiection. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="225"/> Parents muſt euer haue a great regard of their children, in obſeruing three things.
<list>
                     <item>That they bring them vp carefullie in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of God, leaſt they growe graceles. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.4.</item>
                     <item>That they bridle them diſcretly, while they are yong, leaſt they grieue them when they are old. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 22.6.</item>
                     <item>That they prouoke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not too rigorouſly at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie time, leaſt they diſcourage them. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.21.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:37"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="226"/> Such children as are obedient to their parents, ſhall haue this benefite:
<list>
                     <item>They ſhall liue long vpon the earth. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3.</item>
                     <item>They ſhall proſper in all their proceedings. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3.</item>
                     <item>They ſhall haue ioye of their owne children. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 3.6.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="227"/> Children ought to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey their parents,
<list>
                     <item>by the law of God.</item>
                     <item>by the courſe of Nature</item>
                     <item>by the rule of Reaſon.</item>
                  </list> So it bee in the Lord. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</item>
               <item>Maſters ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="228"/> That they haue a maſter aboue that ſeeth all.</item>
                     <item>That they ſhal receiue for the wrong they offer, of him who reſpecteth no perſons.</item>
                     <item>That they bee as carefull to redreſſe their owne faults, as readie to reproue their ſeruants eſcapes.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="229"/> Herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the duetie of Seruants,
<list>
                     <item>To obey their maſters in the Lord, without murmuring.</item>
                     <item>To doo their duetie in ſinglenes of heart, without eye ſeruice. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.6.</item>
                     <item>To ſuffer patientlie rebukes and chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, without reſiſting.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="230"/> Riches of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes be the meanes to cauſe
<list>
                     <item>Impietie:</item>
                     <item>Securitie:</item>
                     <item>Miſerie.</item>
                  </list> As appeares by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of
<list>
                     <item>The yong man. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.22</item>
                     <item>The rich man. <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.</item>
                     <item>Diues and Lazarus. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="231"/> Wicked wealthie worldlings ſhould do well to conſider continuallie of theſe places.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Amos.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eſai.</hi> 65. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</item>
                  </list> A rich man ſhall hardlie enter the kingdome of heauen. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:37"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="232"/> Such as gather their goods by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, briberie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, or ſuch like vnlawfull meanes, what followeth.
<list>
                     <item>They gather them for ſuch (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) as will be good to the poore. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 28.8.</item>
                     <item>The ruſt of their gold &amp; ſiluer (as <hi>Iames</hi> faith) ſhall be a witnes againſt them, and eate their fleſh as it were fire. <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.3.</item>
                     <item>They lie in graue like ſheepe (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) &amp; death gnaweth vpon them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.14.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="233"/> Although worldlings do make their God of their goods, yet the iuſt man doth but eſteeme
<list>
                     <item>Gold and ſiluer to be coloured earth; yea but dung. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.</item>
                     <item>Worldlie wealth and voluptuous fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to be filth and famine.</item>
                     <item>Dignitie &amp; delight, to be ſmoake which the ayre conſumeth ſodainlie.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="234"/> Riches are good in this reſpect.
<list>
                     <item>If wee can vſe and beſtowe them to that end they are giuen vs.</item>
                     <item>If we can as willinglie leaue them, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them.</item>
                     <item>If we ſet not our hearts on them, as they increaſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.10.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>It is a vaine thing for a man to hunt ſo greedilie after worldlie goods, or take ſuch great delight in gathering:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="235"/> Becauſe hee ſhall beare nothing with him when he dieth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.17.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe hee cannot prolong his life with them, though he hath abundance. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.15.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe they will not auaile him in the daie of wrath. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 11.4.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="236"/> Couetouſnes is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temptible in any, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciallie in ſuch, who God hath ſent plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe it is a plague to a rich man to want a liberall heart. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 6.2, &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it is the root of al euil. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it will bee their owne deſtruction in the end. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.5.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="237"/> Riches ſhould not make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if he did think vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god,
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe he is but his ſteward ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a time.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe hee can impoueriſh him as hee did <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.12.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe hee can puniſh him, as hee did <hi>Herod. Acts</hi> 12.23.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:38"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="238"/> God hath choſen in this world
<list>
                     <item>Fooliſh things to confound the wiſe. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27.</item>
                     <item>Weake thinges to confound the mightie. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27.</item>
                     <item>Vile things, &amp; things which are not, to bring to naught things that are. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="239"/> Although begging be a miſerable life, yet we muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the poore:
<list>
                     <item>For hee that deſpiſeth them, deſpiſeth him that made them. <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.5.</item>
                     <item>For God hath made them as his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the triall of our hearts and charitie. <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.21.</item>
                     <item>For God hath choſen the poore in this world, that they ſhould bee rich in faith &amp; heires of his kingdom. <hi>Ia.</hi> 2.5</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="240"/> Aduerſitie and pouertie, is oftentimes ſent of God.
<list>
                     <item>For triall of our faith,</item>
                     <item>For amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our liues,</item>
                     <item>For neglect of our vocation</item>
                  </list> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.
<list>
                     <item>by <hi>Iob,</hi> whoſe ſatietie of ſubſtance was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>by the prodigal ſonne, who by theſe croſſes was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed.</item>
                     <item>by <hi>Salomons</hi> ſaying: Loue not ſleepe, leſt thou come vnto pouertie. <hi>Pro.</hi> 20 13.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="241"/> We ought to giue to the poore
<list>
                     <item>For the glorie &amp; honor of God <hi>Prouer.</hi> 8.9.</item>
                     <item>For good example to others, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16.</item>
                     <item>For a ſigne of the ſinceritie of our profeſſion. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.18.</item>
                  </list> Giue for
<list>
                     <item>Commandement ſake.</item>
                     <item>Neceſſitie ſake.</item>
                     <item>Nature ſake.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="242"/> It may appeare vnto vs by way of compariſon we ought to giue to the poore, for
<list>
                     <item>If a good man will haue pitie on his beaſt, how much more ought wee to reſpect a Chriſtian. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 12.10.</item>
                     <item>If wee ought to lay downe our liues for our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how much more ought we to relieue the with our goods 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16.</item>
                     <item>If a factor ought to diſpoſe his goodes where his temporall maſter pleaſeth, how much more ought we to diſtribute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where our eternal maſter appointeth.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:38"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="243"/> He that giueth to the poore, muſt beſtowe his beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<list>
                     <item>Secretlie,</item>
                     <item>Liberallie,</item>
                     <item>Cheerefully,
<list>
                           <item>without oſtentation. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.2.</item>
                           <item>according to his abilitie. <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.8</item>
                           <item>without grudging. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 35.10.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="244"/> This aſſurance hath he that giueth to the poore,
<list>
                     <item>He lendeth to the Lord. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 19.17.</item>
                     <item>He ſhall not lacke. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 28.27.</item>
                     <item>He ſhal not want his reward. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="245"/> The poore ought rather to be hidden to feaſtes than the rich:
<list>
                     <item>becauſe ſuch haue moſt need. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</item>
                     <item>becauſe they can make no reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</item>
                     <item>becauſe it is moſt acceptable to God. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="246"/> Feaſting is not amiſſe, ſo it be vſed
<list>
                     <item>In remembrance of Gods benefites. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 8</item>
                     <item>For the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mutual friendſhip. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 8</item>
                     <item>Towards the reliefe of the poore. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 8</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>We would bee more mindful of the poore, if we did but remember how dangerous it is
<list>
                     <item>To hide our eyes from them.</item>
                     <item>To ſtoppe our eares at their crie.</item>
                     <item>To ſhew no mercie at all.</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="247"/> Such ſhall
<list>
                     <item>haue many curſes. <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.27.</item>
                     <item>crie and not bee heard. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 21.13.</item>
                     <item>haue merciles condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.13.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="248"/> Pure religon conſiſts in this:
<list>
                     <item>To viſite the fatherles and widowes in aduerſitie. <hi>Barnard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To followe the example of Chriſt. <hi>Barnard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>To keepe thy ſelfe vnſpotted of the world. <hi>Barnard.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="249"/> Such as will bee perfect Chriſtians in religion, ought not to be
<list>
                     <item>Hot,</item>
                     <item>Cold,</item>
                     <item>Luke-warme.</item>
                  </list> but zealous profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.19.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="250"/> It is is very dangerous to deale craftelie in this world,
<list>
                     <item>becauſe it greatlie offendeth God, who is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of truth.</item>
                     <item>becauſe it defraudeth a mans neighbour with a ſhewe of honeſt meaning.</item>
                     <item>becauſe it deſtroieth the deceiuer in the end. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:39"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="251"/> Hypocrites may well iuggle with the world, but they cannot deceiue theſe three.
<list>
                     <item>God.</item>
                     <item>Death.</item>
                     <item>the Diuell.
<list>
                           <item>For he ſeeth their ſecrets, and will one day reueale all.</item>
                           <item>For he commeth of a ſodaine, and will de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroy them with all.</item>
                           <item>For hee waites for their ſoules to reward them for all.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="252"/> An hypocrite is reſembled to theſe 3. things. <hi>Barn.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>A Sheepe in skinne.</item>
                     <item>A Foxe in ſubtiltie.</item>
                     <item>A Wolfe in crueltie.
<list>
                           <item>He talketh ſmoothlie.</item>
                           <item>He intendeth craftelie.</item>
                           <item>He attempteth villanie.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>We be to you hypocrites.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="253"/> Truth is almoſt excellent treaſure, and worthie to be
<list>
                     <item>Honoured.</item>
                     <item>Imbraced:</item>
                     <item>Aduanced:
<list>
                           <item>becauſe it ouercommeth all things.</item>
                           <item>becauſe it defendeth all things.</item>
                           <item>becauſe it in dureth for euer.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="254"/> Such as delight in lying, ſhould but remember the
<list>
                     <item>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>or of it.</item>
                     <item>Euill of it.</item>
                     <item>End of it.
<list>
                           <item>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>led of the diuels ſowing.</item>
                           <item>It is abomination before the Lord.</item>
                           <item>It procureth ſorow to his owne ſoule at laſt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="255"/> This diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of lying.
<list>
                     <item>When one doth accuſtome it he ſhall ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome leaue it.</item>
                     <item>When he ſaith troth, he ſhall hardlie bee beleeued.</item>
                     <item>When he is knowne to be ſuch a one, the better ſort will abhorre him.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="256"/> He is happie that in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication hath an eye in feare
<list>
                     <item>to Gods maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie:</item>
                     <item>to his brothers frailtie:</item>
                     <item>to his own ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetie:
<list>
                           <item>becauſe it is fearfull to fall into his hands. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.13.</item>
                           <item>becauſe it is the eaſieſt thing of a thouſand to offend him.</item>
                           <item>becauſe he muſt giue accompt of euerie idle word.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="257"/> Our communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ought to be yea and nay, yet we may lawfullie ſweare
<list>
                     <item>For the glorie and worſhip of God. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 19.</item>
                     <item>For co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of truth &amp; equitie. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.</item>
                     <item>For diſcharge of our conſcience, being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie called.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="258"/> The Magiſtrate maie lawfullie require an oth: ſo it be done for the maintenance of
<list>
                     <item>Iuſtice:</item>
                     <item>Iudgement:</item>
                     <item>Truth:</item>
                  </list> but wee ought not to ſweare
<list>
                     <item>vainlie,</item>
                     <item>lightly,</item>
                     <item>raſhlie,
<list>
                           <item>when there is no cauſe at all.</item>
                           <item>vpon euerie ſmall occaſion.</item>
                           <item>without good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:39"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="259"/> 
                  <hi>Who ſhall inherite heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaith Dauid.)</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>He that hath cleane hands and a pure heart.</item>
                     <item>He that hath not lift vp his mind to vanitie.</item>
                     <item>He that hath not ſworne to deceiue his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="260"/> The miſchiefes that inſue of Lecherie are manie, if we conferre the beginning with the end. <hi>Barn.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>At firſt it tickleth the fleſh with tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</item>
                     <item>Afterward it poyſoneth the minde with filthie delights.</item>
                     <item>And laſt of al by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenting to ſinne, and willingnes to worke wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes withall, both bodie and ſoule are ouercome.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="261"/> The ſinne of Lecherie is the pleaſanteſt to the diuell.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe it hurteth both bodie and ſoule.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe he was neuer touched with it, being a ſpirit and no bodie.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it bringeth on a heape of other ſinnes withall.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="262"/> The lecherous man in his life is three waies tormented.
<list>
                     <item>with the heate of the harlot.</item>
                     <item>with the paine of his hurt.</item>
                     <item>with the worme of his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="263"/> The ſonne of <hi>Syracke</hi> ſaith there are 3. things which his ſoule hateth.
<list>
                     <item>A poore man that is proud.</item>
                     <item>A rich man that is a lier.</item>
                     <item>An old adulterer that doteth.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="264"/> There be three ſpeciall reaſons, that fornication ſhould be eſchewed. <hi>Beza.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe it defileth the bodie with a peculiar kinde of filthines.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe a fornicator is ſacriligious, for that our bodies are conſecrated to God.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe wee ought both in bodie and ſoule to ſerue him, who hath ſaued vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>This brieflie is to be obſerued in a whore. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 5.
<list>
                     <item>She brings a man to a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of bread.</item>
                     <item>She hunts for the precious life of him.</item>
                     <item>She leades him the hie waie to hell.</item>
                  </list>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="265"/> She is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<list>
                     <item>to a dogge.</item>
                     <item>to a ſowe.</item>
                     <item>to dung.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 26.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:40"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="266"/> A whore is to be abandoned if it were but for theſe cauſes:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe God hath forbidden anie ſuch to be ſuffered. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.17.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe ſhe increaſeth the tranſgreſſors among men. <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.28.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe ſhe enuieth honeſt and vertuous women. 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 16.42.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="267"/> There bee three things maie terrifie a theefe in his lewd attempts.
<list>
                     <item>The precept God hath ſet downe.</item>
                     <item>The poſitiue lawe of this land.</item>
                     <item>The importable iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come.</item>
                  </list> that is,
<list>
                     <item>Thou ſhalt not ſteale. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</item>
                     <item>Death of bodie.</item>
                     <item>Deſtruction both of bodie and ſoule.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="268"/> A theefe by following one (that is the diuell) he offendeth three.
<list>
                     <item>Hee diſpleaſeth God,</item>
                     <item>He hurteth his neighbor.</item>
                     <item>He hateth his own ſoule,
<list>
                           <item>by breaking his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</item>
                           <item>by taking away his right.</item>
                           <item>by following ſin. <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="269"/> This inconuenience commeth of idlenes:
<list>
                     <item>When one is rooted in it, it will hardlie be remoued.</item>
                     <item>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath the end of his luſt it wilbe moſt lothſome.</item>
                     <item>When he is ſo idle the diuell is moſt occupied.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="270"/> There bee three things that grieued the wiſeman.
<list>
                     <item>A man of warre that ſuffereth pouertie.</item>
                     <item>Men of vnderſtanding that are not ſet by.</item>
                     <item>When one departeth from righteouſnes to ſinne.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 26.29.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="271"/> God puniſheth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their ſinnes with three kind of plagues, which commonlie goe together.
<list>
                     <item>Warre,</item>
                     <item>Famine,</item>
                     <item>Peſtilence,</item>
                  </list> and where he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth 3. benefites,
<list>
                     <item>Peace.</item>
                     <item>Plentie.</item>
                     <item>Salubritie.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="272"/> Chriſtian Souldiers fight but faintlie, if they want theſe weapons.
<list>
                     <item>The ſhield of faith</item>
                     <item>The helmet of hope.</item>
                     <item>The ſword of the ſpirit.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="273"/> Euerie Chriſtian Souldier hath three enemies to encounter with.
<list>
                     <item>The lewd affections of themſelues. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.1.</item>
                     <item>The euill prouocations of the pleope.</item>
                     <item>The daily ſuggeſtions of Sathan.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.12.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:40"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="274"/> There were three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſpared in the old lawe from going on warfare.
<list>
                     <item>He that was betrothed to a maide. <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.7.</item>
                     <item>He that was but new maried. <hi>Deu.</hi> 24.5.</item>
                     <item>He that was faint hearted. <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.8.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="275"/> God ſendeth raine, cold, heate, tempeſt, and ſuch like oftentimes,
<list>
                     <item>To puniſh man.</item>
                     <item>To profite the earth.</item>
                     <item>To declare his fauour towards man.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 37.13. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="276"/> One may lawfullie eate fleſh at all times, ſo it be done
<list>
                     <item>without ſcruple or doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</item>
                     <item>without offence of our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                     <item>without breach of godlie or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>For euery creature of God is good, and nothing ought to be refuſed, if it be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with thankes-giuing.</hi> 1. Tim. 4.4.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="277"/> Our meates are ſanctified to vs by the word of God and praier. <hi>Beza.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe we confeſſe &amp; acknowledge that God is the maker &amp; giuer of thoſe creatures which we vſe.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe wee are of the number of thoſe, who through Chriſtes benefite, haue recouered that right ouer all creatures, which <hi>Adam</hi> loſt by his fall.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe by our praiers, wee craue of the Lord that we may vſe thoſe meats with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which we receiue at his hands.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="278"/> Such as by their doctrine will make difference of meates the ſame may be called diuelliſh or deceiptfull in three reſpects. <hi>Beza.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Becauſe the teachers of them make lawes of things which are not their owne: for GOD created the meates.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe they ouerthrowe with their decrees the end wherefore they were made of GOD, to wit, that we ſhould vſe them.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe by this meanes they robbe GOD of his glorie, who will bee honored in the vſe of them.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:41"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="280"/> Our beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ought to be vſed
<list>
                     <item>To our better, reuerentlie.</item>
                     <item>To our equall, louinglie.</item>
                     <item>To our vnderling, lowlie.</item>
                  </list> We ought to call
<list>
                     <item>our elder, father.</item>
                     <item>our yonger brother.</item>
                     <item>Euery man, our neibor.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="281"/> Mariage was inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for three ends.
<list>
                     <item>For a remedie againſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie.</item>
                     <item>For the propagation of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</item>
                     <item>For the conſolation of man and woman.</item>
                  </list> It is
<list>
                     <item>allowed of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes.</item>
                     <item>commended by the Prophets.</item>
                     <item>followed of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Men are made chaſt three manner of waies. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.12.
<list>
                     <item>by Nature,</item>
                     <item>by Arte,</item>
                     <item>by Grace,
<list>
                           <item>Such as are ſo borne of their mothers bellie.</item>
                           <item>Such as bee made chaſt by men.</item>
                           <item>Such as haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues chaſt for heauen.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="282"/> We haue great cauſe to reioyce at theſe daies more than our prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe Chriſt hath made eaſie vnto vs, that importable yoke they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect too. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.31.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe he hath brought vs the glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of ſaluation, which they longed to ſee. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe many Prophets and righteous men haue deſired to ſee theſe daies. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.17.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="283"/> Although honeſt mirth be tollerable, yet fooliſh or exceſſiue mirth is
<list>
                     <item>Vaine:</item>
                     <item>Wicked:</item>
                     <item>Dangerous:
<list>
                           <item>becauſe ſuch mirth ſhal be mingled with mourning, and the ende of ſuch ioy is lamentation.</item>
                           <item>becauſe thereby wee cleane forget the means that ſhould make vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber our miſerie. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.4.</item>
                           <item>becauſe our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, wo bee to them that now laugh, for they ſhall waile and weepe. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.25.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:41"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="284"/> There be three kind of fooles.
<list>
                     <item>Such as are naturallie borne without wit, &amp; thoſe thoſe (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) are a griefe to the father, &amp; a heauines to her that bare them. <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.21, 25.</item>
                     <item>Such as become fooles, and are ſo contented to be counted in this world, that they may bee wiſe in the world to come. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</item>
                     <item>Such as are giuen ouer to their owne luſts, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low al kind of filthines; theſe are they whom <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> calleth fooles, who lewdlie ſaie in their hearts (as they falſlie thinke) there is no God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53.1.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="285"/> A wiſe man is noted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned three maner of waies.
<list>
                     <item>By diſcreet ſilence:</item>
                     <item>By modeſt ſpeach:</item>
                     <item>By ſober life:
<list>
                           <item>
                              <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="286"/> For (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) a foole by holding his peace is counted wiſe <hi>Prouer.</hi> 27.28. not that any ſhould bee reſtrained of ſpeach: but that they ſhould obſerue oportunitie in ſpeaking. Hereof ſaith the Philoſopher, <hi>Qui neſcit tacere, neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit loqui.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>For it is proper to fooles to bee full of fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous talke: but hee that hath know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (ſaith the Wiſe man) ſpareth his words. <hi>Prouer.</hi> 17.27.</item>
                           <item>For he that is heauenlie wiſe indeed, will (as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith) ſhew by conuerſation his workes in meeknes of wiſedome. <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.13.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="287"/> Sicknes is verie neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for man:
<list>
                     <item>Becauſe thereby he is put in minde of his owne frailtie. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.4.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe thereby he ſhall bee better incited to call vppon God. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 20.2.</item>
                     <item>Becauſe it is a teſtimonie vnto him of the loue of God. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12 6.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="288"/> He that is loath to frame himſelfe to dye, eſpeciallie in ſicknes, doth ſhewe himſelfe
<list>
                     <item>Vnnaturall:</item>
                     <item>Vnwiſe:</item>
                     <item>Wretched:
<list>
                           <item>becauſe he ſo little deſires to be at home with his heauenlie father, conſidering hee is here but as a ſtranger and a pilgrime. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.13.</item>
                           <item>becauſe hee taketh felicitie in the vanitie of this world, conſidering the faſhion of it goes away. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.13.</item>
                           <item>becauſe hee had rather ſtill liue to augment his miſerie, than frame himſelfe by a godlie ende, to imbrace eternall bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3272:42"/>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="289"/> In our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes we ought to remember
<list>
                     <item>To ſeeke to God to purge our ſinnes, which are the chiefe cauſe of all our diſeaſes.</item>
                     <item>To vſe the helpe of the Phiſitian, as a meane by whom God worketh.</item>
                     <item>To diſpoſe our temporall goodes, where they may make moſt to his glorie that gaue them.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="290"/> For a man to make his Will, in ſicknes or health, it is
<list>
                     <item>Lawfull;</item>
                     <item>Godlie;</item>
                     <item>Neceſſarie;
<list>
                           <item>becauſe the Lord willed <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to put his houſe in order before he died 2. <hi>King,</hi> 20.1.</item>
                           <item>becauſe his minde being quiet in worldlie matters, he ſhall the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter applie it to heauenlie motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</item>
                           <item>becauſe a good ſtay being made, it ſhall cut off occaſion of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that may happen afterward</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="291"/> The mindes of men are verie mutable, and their opinions (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie ſuch as be peruerſe) are verie ſcrupulous to pleaſe: for
<list>
                     <item>He that did well, offended ſome, and yet was an Apoſtle. <hi>Paul.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24.</item>
                     <item>He that did worſe, pleaſed many, and yet was but a Beaſt. <hi>Herod. Acts.</hi> 12.22.</item>
                     <item>He that did beſt of all, could not pleaſe al, and yet was a God. <hi>Chriſt. Ioh.</hi> 10.20.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="292"/> 
                  <hi>England</hi> hath 3. eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciall cauſes to be conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuallie thankful to God for,
<list>
                     <item>The free paſſage of the Goſpell:</item>
                     <item>The bleſſed time of Peace:</item>
                     <item>The godly Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof.</item>
                  </list> which
<list>
                     <item>Paſſage</item>
                     <item>Peace,</item>
                     <item>Prince,</item>
                  </list> the Lord for his mercie ſake ſtill
<list>
                     <item>proſper.</item>
                     <item>preſerue.</item>
                     <item>protect.</item>
                  </list> Amen.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3272:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
